네가 그녀의 방문을 주선했다면
별로 재미 없었을거다
It could not have served your interests
better if you had arranged her visit.
모든 성직자들이 그를 반대하여 일어나고
의회는 그를 비난한다
The priesthood is aroused against him.
The council condemns him.
심지어 백성들조차 공공연히 그의 수치에 대해 말한다
Even the people talk openly of his shame.
전하께서는 제 생각과 같군요
Your Highness is reflecting
my own thoughts.
나는 이런 기회를 무시하는 바보일거다
I would be a fool
to ignore such an opportunity.
전하께서는 이번처럼 영원히 다른 누군가를 기다려야 할지도 모르죠．
You might have to wait forever
for another one like this.
난 헤즈라이와 자독을 위해 그들의 문제를 해결해야겠다
I will solve
Hezrai and Zadok's problem for them
그리고 동시에 나의 문제도
and at the same time, my own.
또한 오히려, 요압, 너의 도움으로 해결해야 할 문제다
Or rather, this is a problem that you, Joab,
with a little help, will solve.
명령만 하십시오, 전하
I await your command, Highness.
(gong)
폐하께서 절 불러오라 명령하셨습니까?
Your Majesty commanded me
to attend upon her?
네가 도착하는데는 아주 충분한 시간이지
널 데려오기 위해 한시간 전에 타칸을 보냈다
It took you long enough to get here.
I sent Takyan to bring you an hour ago.
10분전에 도착했습니다, 폐하께서 바라신다면
Ten minutes ago, if Your Majesty pleases.
들어오라, 나와 이야기 하면서 거기 서있지 마라
Come in. Don't stand there
arguing with me.
폐하를 어떻게 모실까요？
In what way can I serve Your Majesty?
넌 나를 이스라엘 밖으로 안전하게 수행할수 있다
You can arrange
for my safe conduct out of Israel.
그렇게 날 바라보지 마라
내가 말한대로 하도록
Stop looking at me like that!
Do as I tell you!
- 그러나 언젭니까? 폐하
- 지금, 오늘, 당장
- But when, Your Majesty?
- Now. Today. This minute.
제가 충격을 주더라도 폐하께서는 날 용서하시겠지요?
Your Majesty will pardon me
if I seem shocked...
내가 하고 싶은 모든 것을 너와 먼저 상의해야 하느냐？
Do I have to consult you first
concerning everything I wish to do?
폐하께서는 목적을 달성하지 않고 가실겁니까?
Your Majesty would go without
accomplishing her purpose?
내가 오고 가는 문제는 내가 결정한다
Permit me to decide the question
of my comings and goings.
제가 과감히 폐하의 사생활을 언급 하더라도 날 용서해 주시겠지요?
Your Majesty will forgive me if I venture
to touch upon her personal, private affairs.
요점을 말하라, 바틀러
Get to the point, Baltor.
저는 폐하의 변화를 감지했습니다
약해지는 모습을....
I have sensed a change
in Your Majesty. A softening.
현실을 피하고 싶어하는 욕망을.....
A desire to evade reality.
넌 내가 사랑에 빠져 있다고 추궁하고 있느냐？
그러하냐?
You are accusing me
of being in love with him? Is that it?
여기는 이집트와 이스라엘의 국경 지대이다
This is the borderland that lies between
the countries of Egypt and Israel.
전 그와 같은 경우가 아니라, 폐하의 목적을 위한것이길 바랍니다
I hope for Your Majesty's own sake
that such is not the case.
나사렛 예수 탄생하시기 천년전에도 지금처럼 국경이었다
As it is today, so it was 1,000 years
before the birth of Jesus of Nazareth.
그리고 그와 같은 경우라면
And if such is the case,
심지어 그 당시에도 증오와 대립의 불길로 불타올랐다
Even then, these boundaries
were kept ablaze
인간으로서 내 생애에 처음으로 가지는 나의 권리를 부정하느냐?
do you deny me the right
for the first time in my life to be human?
with the fires of hatred and conflict.
양측은 서로 첩자들의 정탐능력이 뛰어났지만,
Each side prided themselves
on the efficiency of their spies
파라오와 나라의 국익보다도 개인의 감정들을
May I remind Your Majesty that
you cannot put your personal feelings
항상 경계를 게을리 하지않고 자신들을 지켰다
but kept themselves
always on the alert.
추스리지 못하는 폐하를 상기하게 될지도 모르죠
above the Pharaoh
and the good of your country?
다비드의 아들이며 후계자인 이스라엘의 왕자 아도니아에
의해 통솔되는 다비드의 병사들
Soldiers of David, commanded by his
son and heir Adonijah, prince of Israel.
날 가르치려 들지마라, 바틀러
Don't lecture me, Baltor.
폐하께서는 한때 제게 여자로서 사치할 여유가 없다고 말씀하셨죠
Your Majesty once told me that you could
not afford the luxury of being a woman,
그렇게 항상 여왕인점을 기억하도록 강요당했죠
that always you were forced
to remember that you are a queen,
- 길을 따라 전차가 옵니다.
- 어떤 놈인진 몰라도, 저 멍청한놈을 세워.
- A chariot moving along the road.
- Stop the fool, whoever he is.
폐하의 유일한 사랑도, 생각도 의무가 되야 합니다
and that your only love,
your only thought, must be your duty.
폐하께서는 예루살렘에 오셨습니다
Your Majesty came to Jerusalem
폐하께서 한때 증오했던 적을 무너뜨릴 수단을 찾아서！
in search of a means to destroy
an enemy whom you once hated!
그래, 바틀러
Yes, Baltor.
난 현실을 도피하려 했다
I have been trying to evade reality.
- 솔로몬 왕자님.
- 형님이 여기 계신가?
- Prince Solomon.
- Is my brother here?
내가 왔던 목적을 잊으려고 하는걸 깨달았다
I have found myself trying to forget
the purpose for which I came,
아도니아 왕자님은 언덕위에 계십니다.
저를 따라 오십시요.
Prince Adonijah is at the top of the hill.
Follow me.
악몽을 잊으려고 하는것처럼
as one would try to forget an evil dream.
난 그가 몰락하는게 싫었다
I have been reluctant
to make an end of him.
가장 자비로운 방법은 칼로 빠르고 강하게 찔러 죽이는것입니다
The most merciful way to kill is to thrust
quickly and strongly with a knife.
솔로몬!
대체 뭐하러 왔나?
Solomon! What are you doing here?
사냥감이 우리가 오기전 보다 더 멀리 있는것 처럼 보입니다
It seems to me that we are no nearer a kill
than we were before we came.
예루살렘에 가는 길에 이집트인들이
다시 출몰하고 있다는 연락을 받았습니다．
On my way to Jerusalem, we got word
the Egyptians were on the prowl again.
형님께 어느정도 도움이 필요할것 같아서요
I thought you might need some help.
틀렸어, 바틀러
난 요 며칠간 솔로몬을 어떻게 무너뜨릴지 알아냈다
You are wrong, Baltor. I have known
for days how to destroy Solomon.
너는 싸움에서 공을 세우는것 보다
노래를 부르는게 더 어울려
You are better suited to singing songs
than exploits in battle.
아버지 다비드는 노래를 잘 부르지만
또한 강한 전사이기도 합니다
Our father David was a singer of songs,
but he's also a mighty warrior.
이스라엘의 위대한 여호와 앞에서 라곤의 의식을
Suppose I get his permission to hold the
rites of Rha-Gon upon the soil of Israel,
개최하는 허락을 얻는다고 생각해봐
to set up a pagan god
in the face of the great Jehovah,
- 이집트인들이 어디에 있습니까?
- 그들은 우리가 잠들어있는 동안
- Where are the Egyptians?
- They thought to trap me,
이스라엘 사람들에게 다른 어떤신도 두지 말라고 명령하는 유일신 앞에
the one god who commands the Israelites
to have no other god before him?
숙영지에 뛰어들어 우릴 죽이려는 함정을 꾸몄다
그러나 우리는 잠들지 않았지
to rush in on our camp and kill us
while we slept, but we're not sleeping.
그것은 어떤 성난 목소리들보다 그를 반대하는 좋은 사유가 될겁니다
That would cause more
than angry murmurings against him.
성직자들과 백성들은 솔로몬에 대적하여 들고 일어설것입니다．
The priests and the people
would rise up against Solomon.
그래, 바틀러
Yes, Baltor.
그의 백성들이 그를 몰락시키겠지
His own people
would accomplish his end.
내가 아직도 시바의 여왕인 것에 만족하느냐？
Are you satisfied now
that I am still the Queen of Sheba?
폐하
Majesty.
명령을 내리십시요.
Give me your orders.
아우여! 이것은 놀이가 아니야.
This is not your kind of game, brother.
나는 결코 놀이따위로 생각하지 않습니다. 형님 옆에서 싸우겠습니다
I never thought of it as a game.
I fight by your side.
- 건투를 빈다. 솔로몬.
- 하나님의 가호가 있기를, 아도니아여.
- Then the sword of victory, Solomon.
- And the shield of God, Adonijah.
얼마나 많은 날들을, 내가 당신을 사랑한다고 이야기할까？
How many times
shall I tell you that I love you?
산개해서 모두 죽여라
Spread out, and kill them all.
계속, 내가 그것을 믿을때까지 해주세요
Over and over,
until you make me believe it.
그럴것이오
I will.
그러나 당신은 그렇게 많은 여자들 알고 있어요
But you have known so many loves.
(whooping)
나는 손을 잡고 당신을 데려갈것이오
I will take you by the hand
(yelling)
성전에서, 모든 이스라엘 앞에서, 결혼식에서 난 나의 사랑을 맹세하겠오
and in the temple, before all Israel,
I'll pledge you my love in marriage.
당신의 하렘에 날 가두려고? 당신의 여자들과 사랑을 다투라고?
To shut me away in your harem?
To share your love?
아니오, 당신과 함께 나의 왕좌를 공유 할것이오
No, to share my throne with you.
당신이 날 존중 한다지만 난 이미 여왕이에요
You honour me, but I am already a queen.
우리 인생을 합치는것처럼 우리 영토도 합칠것이오
We will join our lands
as we will join our lives.
- 지금 공격한다.
- 공격.
- Now we attack.
- Attack.
결코 이루어질수 없는 꿈이에요, 우리 사이엔 대단히 많은 문제가 있어요
A dream that can never be.
Too much stands between us.
우리 사이에 아무 문제도 없을것이오
Nothing must stand between us.
우리 신들도 문제 없나요?
Not even our gods?
이 순간이 올줄 알았어요, 우리는 동일한 신을 믿지 않기에
I knew this moment would come, for the
things we believe in are not the same.
난 당신이 여호와를 받아들이러 오기를 바랬다오
I had hoped that in time
you would come to accept Jehovah.
이스라엘의 왕으로서, 당신은 자신을 위해 백성들의 신을 버릴수 있나요?
As king of Israel, would you abandon
the god of your people for mine?
아직도 내겐 희망이 있오
Still I dared hope.
내사랑,
난 이스라엘을 떠나야 해요
My love, I must leave Israel.
왜? 왜?
당신을 가게 할수 없오
Why? Why? I cannot let you go.
해마다 하는 라곤의 축제를 할때가 돌아왔어요
The time has come
for the yearly feast of Rha-Gon.
당신은 여기 이스라엘에서 축제를 할수 있도록 허락해 줄수 있나요?
Can you grant me permission
to hold it here in Israel?
그건 신성모독이오
It would be a sacrilege.
그때는 전 어디에서라도 축제를 축하하러 가야해요
Then I must go to celebrate it elsewhere.
아시나요?
우리 사이에 있는 것은 물리칠수 없어요
You see? You cannot banish
what stands between us.
아니오, 기다리시오, 내말을 들어요
틀림없이 방법이 있을거요
No, wait. Listen to me.
There must be a way to...
안돼요!
No!
(screams)
퇴각신호를 불어라
Sound the retreat.
(screams)
도와줘요!
Help! Help! The king!
도와줘요! 경비원! 요시아!
Help! Guard! Josiah!
요압?
Joab.
다시 한번, 파라오는 이 아도니아의 이름을 기억하게 될것이다
Once again, the Pharaoh will have reason
to remember the name of Adonijah.
괜찮습니까?
Are you safe, sire?
그 주검의 피로 이름을 쓰게 해주지
Let him write it in the blood of his dead.
이 땅은 너무 오랫동안 피에 젖었어
Too long
this soil has been bathed in blood.
전쟁이 끝나고 나니, 피때문에 입맛을 잃어버렸느냐？
Have you lost your taste for blood
now that the battle is over?
그를 보낸 사람에게 보낼것이오
We'll deliver him to the one who sent him.
따라오라!
(guard) Come on!
승리의 영광을 보고 난 후에
After seeing the glory of victory,
평화의 영광은 그 스스로를 알리지요
the glory of peace makes itself known.
평화는 여자들과 아이들을 위해 있다
Peace is for women and children.
내입의 이집트인들의 악취를 씻자꾸나
Let me cleanse my mouth
of the stench of the Egyptians.
폐하를 해치지 않도록 해주신 모든 신들께 감사드립니다
Thank all the gods you are not harmed.
이스라엘의 왕자에 의한 새로운 승리를 위하여
To a new victory
won by the Prince of Israel.
내 인생에서 처음으로, 난....
난 내 자신을 생각하지 않았다
For the first time in my life,
I... I had no thought for myself.
- 전사 아도니아 왕자님을 위하여.
- 아도니아님을 위하여
- To the warrior prince, Adonijah.
- To Adonijah.
형님에게 영광이!
이스라엘의 영광을 드높였군요
To your glory, brother.
May it increase the glory of Israel.
난 오로지 그만을 염려했어
I feared only for him.
만일 아버지의 명령이 나를 막지 않았다면 더 큰 영광이 있었을거다．
There would be greater glory if I were
not shackled by command of my father.
'방어만 하고 결코 공격하지 마라'
Defend but never attack.
내가 왕이되면 적의 성역들을 없앨것이다
When I am king, there will be no
privileged sanctuaries for my enemies.
(horses approaching)
그들의 도시에서도 모두 없앨거야.
I'll pursue them into their own cities.
- 우리는 그들을 개처럼 몰아낼겁니다.
- 우리는 그들을 쫒아낼것입니다.
- We'll hunt them down like dogs.
- We'll rout them out.
전하, 이자를 사체들 사이에서 발견했습니다. 그러나 그는 이집트인이 아닙니다.
Highness, this one was found
among the dead, but he is no Egyptian.
너희는 저쪽으로, 너흰 날 따르라
(Josiah) You men, that way.
The rest, follow me.
그를 내려놓아라.
Put him down.
파라오에게 용병들이 있지만 난 그와 같은자를 본적이 없다.
The Pharaoh has mercenaries,
but I have never seen one like him.
- 어디서 왔나?
- 나는 시바 여왕폐하께
- From where do you come?
- I have the honour to serve Her Majesty.
서훈을 받았소.
- 시바 여왕?
- The Queen of Sheba.
- The Queen of Sheba?
우리는 시바로부터 멀리 떨어져 있다. 800리그의 거리야
We're a long way from the land of Sheba.
800 leagues.
내가 자비를 구해 변명할 것으로 기대하는가？
Are you expecting me to plead for mercy?
여왕은 어디로 갔습니까? 저~, 전 호위병입니다
Where goes the Queen of Sheba
there go I, a soldier of her guard.
난 이스라엘에서 당신의 가치때문에 당신의 증오를 그냥 간과했오
I have overlooked your hatred
because of your value to Israel.
- 난 결코 당신을 대적하지 않기로 맹세했오
- 난 맹세하지 않았다
- I pledged never to turn against you.
- I asked for no pledge.
왜 시바인들은 이집트인들과 함께 이스라엘을 대적하는가?
Why does a Sheban
fight with Egyptians against Israel?
그러나 오늘밤 당신은 이스라엘에 대적하여 일을 벌렸오
But tonight you raised your hand
against the life of Israel.
나는 여왕의 명령이 있는곳에서 싸웁니다
I fight where my queen commands.
그리고 군사들을 이끌고 야만인들을 무찌르는 일은 여왕폐하를 기쁘게 하는 일이오
And it pleased my queen to lead
her troops against a band of barbarians.
너와 시바의 허튼 계집은 이스라엘의 미명을 더럽혔다
You and your Sheban slut
have defiled the fair name of Israel.
단지 난 우리나라를 오염으로부터 보호할려고 했을뿐이다
I sought only to preserve our country
from your contamination.
경의의 증표로 이 용감한 여왕의 병사를 무덤으로 보내주겠다
I'll send your hide to this brave queen
of yours as a token of my esteem.
안됩니다, 한사람의 군인으로서 그에게 경의를 표합시다
No. Grant him the respect
one soldier should have for another.
내 정맥에 다비드의 피가 흐르는 것처럼 당신에게도 흐르기에
Only because the blood of David
flows through your veins as well as mine,
목숨은 살려주겠소, 그러나 당신을 이스라엘에서 영원히 추방하겠오
I grant you your life,
but I banish you from Israel forever.
그의 상처를 묶어줘.
Bind up his wounds.
고맙게 생각하지만 넌 너 자신의 생명에 신경을 써야 할걸
I suppose I should be grateful, but you
should be concerned with your own life -
그를 살려 주어라.
So spare him.
벌써 시바의 독으로 생명을 잃지 않았다면,
if it has not already been lost
to the poison of Sheba.
나의 친애하는 아우의 따뜻한 마음에 대한 경의로서
Out of regard for the tender heart
of my dear brother.
- 끌어내라, 요시아
- 그를 데려가, 그리고 그도
- Remove him, Josiah.
- Take him, and him.
이 여왕은 우리 국경들을 가로질러 병사들을 인솔해
This queen amuses herself
by leading men across our borders
이스라엘 사람들을 살해하는걸 서커스 구경하듯이 즐기는군
to slay Israelites
as she might attend a circus.
여왕이 여기서 많은 재미를 봤는지 궁금하군요?
I doubt if she found
much amusement here.
당신이 허락했던 부정의 소산으로부터 자신을 깨끗이 하기를 간청합니다
I charge you to cleanse yourself of
this iniquity you have permitted to spawn.
헤즈라이.
Hezrai.
우상숭배하는 이 여자를 버리십시요
그 여자가 세운 가증한 것을 없애십시요
Abjure this woman of her idolatries. Tear
down the abomination she has erected.
난 그녀 종교의 신성한 의식을 개최할수 있도록 허락했오
I have given her permission
to hold the sacred rite of her own religion.
무엇이 왕의 재상을 여기까지 오게 했는가?
명령이 더 있나?
What brings the king's chancellor here?
More orders?
아닙니다, 전하! 만일 그렇다면 행복한 임무겠지요
No, Highness. If that were so,
mine would be a far happier mission.
이교도의 주연을!
떠들썩한 술잔치를!
A pagan revel! An orgy!
난 내가 한일에 대하여 사과하지 않겠오
I have no apology to make
for what I have done.
당신의 아버지, 다비드께서 임종을 맞이했습니다
Your father, King David,
lies at the point of death.
내가 명령한데로 할것이오
As I have commanded, so shall it be.
당신은 하나님의 계명과 그분의 명령을 어겼오
You have broken God's covenant
and his commandment:
혼수상태에서 의식을 회복하지 못하고 있습니다
He lapsed into a coma
and has not regained consciousness.
"내 앞에 어떤 신도 두지 말라"
"Thou shalt have no other gods
before me."
의사들이 왕자님을 모시고 올때까지도 장담하지 못하는 상태입니다.
His physicians could give me
no word of hope to bring you.
"너 자신을 위하여 어떤 상도 새기지 말라"
"Thou shalt not make unto thyself
any graven images."
요시아, 예루살렘으로 간다.
Josiah, we ride to Jerusalem.
"죽이지 말라."
그러나 나를 대항하여 살인미수를 저질렀오
"Thou shalt not kill."
But murder was attempted against me.
- 이스라엘 왕, 아도니아님 만세.
- 아도니아님 만세, 국왕폐하 만세
- Hail Adonijah, King of Israel.
- Hail Adonijah. Hail the king.
시바가 도망가지 않았다면, 암살자들이 그녀를 살려두지 않았을것이오
If Sheba had not escaped,
the assassins would not have spared her.
왕을 선포하는 것은 왕자님의 권리가 아닙니다.
그 법들은 이렇습니다
It is not your right to proclaim the king.
These are the words of the Law:
내가 허락한것은 죄악을 도모한데 따른 가벼운 보상이오
The permission I have granted is poor
compensation for the crime attempted.
"그는 기혼의 물로 기름부음을 받을것이며
"He shall be anointed
with the waters of Gihon
이 여자에 대한 정욕으로 이성을 잃은것처럼 보입니다
It seems that in your lust for this woman,
you have lost your reason.
선지자와 지파의 장로들 앞에서 왕위에 오를것이다"
and crowned in the presence of the
priest and the elders of the tribes."
재상, 그대의 법은 말일지 모르나 나의 법은 검이요
Your law may be the Word, Chancellor.
Mine is the sword.
말 조심하라, 헤즈라이
그것은 그녀를 향한 사랑이다
Choose your words carefully, Hezrai.
It is love I have for her.
아도니아님 만세.
Hail Adonijah.
사랑으로, 난 그녀와 같이 왕좌를 누릴것을 요청했오
Out of love,
I offered to share this throne with her.
그리고 사랑으로, 난 그녀의 의식에 참가할것이오
And out of love, I will attend her ritual.
그런데 넌 왜 가만히 있지?
내가 다비드왕의 올바른 후계자가 아닌가?
And why do you remain silent?
Am I not David's rightful heir?
- 아버지 생각은 전혀 하지 않는군요?
- 인생은 살아있는자를 위한것이다.
- Your first thought is not for our father?
- Life is for the living.
- 내 이야기를 들으시오, 솔로몬
- 난 당신에게 듣고 싶어하는 모든것을 들었오
- Hear me, Solomon.
- I have heard all I want to hear from you.
다비드왕께서 돌아가신다면, 나는 제일 먼저 형님을 인정할것입니다
When I know David is no longer living,
I will be the first to acknowledge you.
그리고 하나님의 음성을 들으시오
Then hear the voice of God.
왕의 옷은 당신에게서 벗겨질것이고
The royal raiment
will be stripped from you.
당신은 후회하며 울부짖을 것이오
You will cry out your repentance,
그러나 당신 백성들의 귀와 마음은 당신에게서 닫혀질것이오
but the ears and hearts of your people
will be closed against you.
따라가겠습니다, 전하
I will follow you, Highness.
그리고 나의 귀는 수다를 떠는 성직자들과 웅얼거리는 노인들에게서 닫혀졌지
And my ears are closed to cackling priests
and mumbling old men.
네가 아니라 내가 왕이라는것을, 명백히 보여주겠다
I will show you
I am king in Israel, not you.
우리는 내일 새벽까지 예루살렘에 도착해야 합니다
We could reach Jerusalem
by dawn tomorrow.
솔로몬이 임종을 보게 하자. 내 생각엔 살아계실것이다.
Let Solomon concern himself with
the dead. My thoughts are for the living.
슬프도다, 솔로몬
- Woe unto you, Solomon.
- (murmuring)
나는 이 시바 여왕에게 볼일이 있어
I have business with this Sheban queen.
그녀를 따라잡으려면 빨리가야 해
We must ride fast to overtake her.
말을 대기해!
Horses!
라곤! 라곤!
(all) Rha-Gon! Rha-Gon!
이랴! 이랴!
Hai! Hai!
Hai! Go!
이랴! 이랴!
Go! Go!
멈춰라!
Halt!
비켜라!
Stand aside.
오 사랑의 신, 생명을주는 라곤이시어, 우리의 말을 들으소서
Hear us, O Rha-Gon,
god of love, giver of life.
우리 몸에 영혼을 주소서
Let thy spirit enter into our bodies.
이스라엘에서는 내가 명령한다
In Israel, I give the orders.
내 숙영지를 방문했던 지난밤에 당신을 만나지 못한것이 유감스럽군
I regret that we did not meet last night
when you visited my encampment.
남자들에게는 강함과 생명력을 주시고
Endow our men with strength and vitality
여자들에게는 영원한 출산의 힘을 주소서
and our women with endless fruitfulness.
당신은 누군가요?
Who are you?
- 이스라엘의 왕이다.
- 거짓말입니다.
- The king of Israel.
- He lies.
어떤놈인지, 사칭하고 있습니다.
Whoever he is, he is an impostor.
왕은 나이를 많이 먹어 쇠약한 노인네입니다
The king is an old man,
weak with the burden of his years.
이집트와 연합한것이 안전하다고 생각되나?
Is that why you thought it safe
to join forces with the Egyptians?
허락해 주시면
저놈들을 길에서 깨끗하게 치워버리겠습니다
Give me leave,
and I will clear them from the road.
지난밤 보다 더 잘할수 있을것으로 생각하는가?
You think you could do better now
than you did last night?
다비드왕은 예루살렘에서 죽었다.
나는 아도니아, 그의 후계자다
David lies dead in Jerusalem.
I, Adonijah, am his heir.
(frenzied singing)
우리는 이스라엘과 연합하기를 원하지 않습니다.
말하게 둬. 발터
- We want no dealings with the Israelites.
- Let him speak, Baltor.
우호적으로 대한다며
우릴 수색하는것이 무슨 호의냐?
- What favour do you seek of me?
- If we were dealing in favours,
(distant drums and singing)
- 네 머리를 가져올수 있었다.
- 그를 죽여라!
- I could bring you the heads of your dead.
- Kill him!
- 네 머리 또한 안전하지 않아
- 조용히 하라, 하란
- Your own head is not too secure.
- Silence, Haran.
난 그대들이 호의운운 하는것을 용납하지 않겠다
하지만 그들을 용서해 주도록 하지
I pursued you not to ask favours
but to grant them.
그러면 이스라엘인들은 시바의 여왕에게 어떤 선물을 줄수 있나요?
And what favour could an Israelite
grant the Queen of Sheba?
그대가 지금 다스리는 것의 두배의 왕국을
A kingdom twice as large
as she now rules.
파라오와 동맹을 끊으시오, 당신의 깃발들을 나의 깃발들 옆에서 날리도록 합시다
Renounce your alliance with the Pharaoh.
Let your banners fly beside mine.
내가 파라오를 정복하면, 당신의 국경에 접하는 그의 모든 땅을 그대에게 주겠소
When I have overthrown him, I will give
you all his lands that border on your own.
나의 문은 닫혔오
My door was closed.
내가 만일 당신의 제의을 거부한다면?
And if I refuse your generosity?
꼭 내 사생활을 침범해야 하오?
Must you intrude upon my privacy?
그러면 파라오를 숨통을 끊을 똑같은 먼지구덩이에
그대를 쳐박아 버릴것이오
Then I will hurl you down into
the same dust that will choke the Pharaoh.
문 닫는것으로 양심을 차단할수 있습니까
Can you shut out your conscience
by closing the door?
무슨 말을 할려고 하오?. 날 혼자 있게 해주시오
Say what you must,
then please leave me alone.
이스라엘과 함께 영광인가, 이집트와 함께 불행인가?
선택은 그대의 몫이오
Yours is the choice.
Glory with Israel, or disaster with Egypt.
내가 한때 알던 사람을 찾아왔어요
I come seeking the man I once knew.
개자식!
You dog!
고귀하고, 온화하고 친절한 남자, 하나님과 함께 걸었던 남자를
The man who was noble, gentle and kind,
the man who walked with God.
네 조상들이 곤충따위를 먹으며
My ancestors sat upon
the throne of a great country
손과 무릎으로 기어다닐때
내 조상들은 거대한 왕국의 왕좌에 있었다
when yours still crawled on their hands
and knees, feeding on insects.
- 그것은 단순한 말에 불과하오, 아비삭
- 제 말을 들어주세요
- Those are mere words, Abishag.
- I entreat you to listen.
그것이 너의 답이냐?
이것이 나의 답이다
- Is that your answer?
- This is my answer.
내가 어렸을때 당신은 온 세상이었고, 전 당신을 흠모했어요
When I was a child,
you were the world and I adored you.
그러나 시간이 흐르고, 흠모가 사랑으로 바뀌었죠
But time passed,
and love changed even as I did.
하란!
Haran!
한 남자를 위한 한 여자의 사랑으로 되어 갔어요
My love became
that of a woman for a man.
그러나 그 남자는 왕이 되었죠
But the man became a king,
이스라엘 왕 만세!
Hail the king of Israel!
그리고 그의 눈에는 그여자가 아직도 어린아이였어요
and in his eyes,
the woman was still a child.
(drums and singing)
당신을 얼마나 강하게 소리쳐 부르는지 아나요
I know how strongly it calls to you.
당신 백성들의 말을 들으세오
제가 사랑으로 당신을 부르는것처럼 그들의 사랑은 당신을 부르고 있어요
Listen to your people. Their love
calls to you, as I call in my love.
예루살렘
- (priest chanting)
- (crowd responding)
제가 아니라 그들의 이야기를 들어 보세요
Listen to them if not to me.
당신과 내 백성들이 인정하든지 말든지, 난 가야하오
Whether you or my people approve,
I must go.
당신은 갈수 없어요
자멸하지 마세요!
You cannot go. Do not destroy yourself!
제발!
I beg of you!
솔로몬
Solomon.
- 늦지 않았소. 아비삭?
- 아직 살아 계십니다.
- Am I in time, Abishag?
- He still lives.
당신의 어머니와 저는 계속 그의 곁에 있었습니다
Your mother and I have been
constantly by his side.
- 우리는 희망을 가져야 하오
- 제 기도에 응답이 있었어요
- We must have hope.
- My prayers have been answered.
당신의 아버지께서 축복을 해줄수 있을때까지
당신은 여기에 있어야 합니다
That you are here while your father
is able to give you his blessing.
- 어머니
- 아들아
- Mother.
- My son.
내 아들아
My son.
절망하지 마세요
Do not despair.
- 희망이 있습니까?
- 심장이 아직 뛰고 있습니다
- Is there hope?
- His heart still beats,
그러나 숨결은 금속에 김도 서리지 않을 정도로 꺼져가고 있습니다
but his breath is so quenched
that it leaves no mist upon the metal.
나의 아버지, 나의 왕이여
My father. My king.
내 기도가 (죽음의) 그림자로부터 당신을 돌아오게 하소서
Let my prayers call you back
from the shadows.
솔로몬, 주님의 평화가 있으라
Solomon, peace of the Lord.
꿈에서, 너의 얼굴은 항상 내앞에 있었다
In my dream,
your face was ever before me.
제가 여기에 있습니다, 아버지
Now I am here, Father.
(tempo quickens)
- 너의 형은 어디에 있느냐?
- 아도니아는 그의 군대와 함께 대기하고 있습니다
- Where is your brother?
- Adonijah was detained with his troops.
(laughter)
항상 군인답구나
Ever the soldier, before all else.
돌아오라는 명령으로 전령을 보내라
Send messages
with my command that he return.
그렇게 하겠습니다
It will be done.
건강이 회복 될때까지 쉬셔야 합니다
Now rest until your strength returns.
- 선지자 나단을 데려오라
- 저는 여기에 있습니다. 왕이시어
- Bring me Nathan the prophet.
- I am here, O King.
12지파의 장로들을 소집하라
Summon the elders of the 12 tribes
and the council.
하나님의 계시를 받았노라
I have had a vision from God.
(wild shrieking)
- 여러분들은 왕의 명령으로 소집되었습니다
- 왕의 말씀을 들으시오
You've been summoned at the king's
command. Hear the words of the king.
아도니아를 데려오기 위해 보낸
전령들에게서 보고가 없느냐?
Has there been no report
from the couriers sent to bring Adonijah?
없습니다. 왕이시어. 아무도 돌아오지 않았습니다
No, sire, none have returned.
그렇다면 그 없이 해야겠구나
Then I must act without him.
40년동안 나는 너희들을 통치했으며
40 years I have reigned over you,
나는 너희들의 아버지였고, 너희는 나의 사랑스런 자녀들이었도다
and I have been your father
and you my beloved children.
너희들의 가슴속에 살아있을 나에 대한 추억들 이외에도
Excepting the memory of me
which will live in your hearts,
'이스라엘의 단일'이라는 업적을 남기고 나는 떠나노라
I leave but one monument to my name:
The unity of Israel.
12지파의 상징이, 각자 권력을 다투는 바람에 한번 분열되었으나
Symbol of the 12 tribes, once separate,
each striving for dominance,
주 하나님이시여, 이 종의 기도를 들으소서
Lord God, hear the prayer of thy servant.
부술수 없는 단일성으로 지금은 함께 단결한 12지파의 장로들이
but now you, the elders of the tribes,
stand before me, banded together,
저는 저의 왕 솔로몬을 그 자신으로부터 구할 힘이 아니었습니다
Mine was not the strength
to save my lord Solomon from himself.
내 앞에 서 있도다
in an indestructible oneness.
그러나 당신은 권능이십니다.
그 분노가 불시에 그를 방문하지 않도록 하소서
But thine is the power.
Let not thy wrath descend upon him.
아합, 그대는 연합된 지파들을 마지막으로 이끌었으며
You were the last to lead your tribe
into the union, Ahab.
그의 마음을 보시고 그를 불쌍히 여기소서
Look into his heart and pity him.
그대의 충실한 서약으로서, 그대의 유일한 아이인 아비삭을 내게 데려왔도다
And as a pledge of your loyalty,
you brought me your only child, Abishag.
그러나 만일 그를 징계 하시고자 한다면, 그 대신에 저를 징계하소서
But if it be thy will to punish him,
visit it upon me in his stead.
나는 그애를 내 딸처럼 사랑했고 소중히 보살폈도다,
I have loved and cherished her
as my own daughter,
내가 사랑했고 소중히 여겼던 이스라엘 처럼,
as I have loved and cherished Israel,
그애는 살아있는 상징이 되어
of which she has become
the living symbol.
제 집에 명예가 되었습니다
She has been an honour to my house.
(shrieking)
그리고 다비드의 가족에게도
And to the household of David.
나의 날은 거의 저물었도다
My day is almost done.
그러나 이스라엘의 날은 아직도 미명이로다
But the day of Israel has hardly dawned.
내 뒤를 이어 왕좌를 이을 후인을 위해 여지를 만드는것이 좋도다
It is well that I make room for another
to follow after me on this throne.
안됩니다. 왕위에 계십시오
No, you stay the king.
안됩니다! 안됩니다!
(crowd) No! No!
- 폐하, 아도니아 왕자님이십니다.
- 아도니아?
- His Highness, Prince Adonijah.
- Adonijah?
폐하! 폐하의 명령이 제게 도달하자마자
Sire, I have driven like a fury
to attend this council
이 회합에 참석키 위해 득달같이 왔나이다
ever since your command reached me.
나의 두 분신을 보라
Behold the two halves of me.
군인이고
The soldier.
그리고 시인이도다
And the poet.
(women screaming)
나는 진정코 양쪽 다 사랑했도다
I have loved you both dearly.
말하라
Tell me.
- 너희들 사이에 무슨 질투가 있느냐?
- 아닙니다. 폐하
- Is there any jealousy between you?
- No, sire.
무슨 질투? 내게 무슨 학자로서 유명해지고자 하는 욕망이 있는가?
Jealousy of what? Have I a desire
to distinguish myself as a scholar?
통치자는 아도니아의 숙명입니다
그리고 저는 진실로 그에게 줄것입니다.
It is Adonijah's destiny to rule,
and I will truly serve him.
창조물의 숙명을 정하는 것은 하나님이시니라, 나의 아들아
It is God who decrees
the destinies of his creatures, my son.
내가 죽음의 근처에 가로 누었던 것 처럼,
As I lay close to death,
어둠을 뚫고 그 위대한 목소리는 나를 불러 말씀하셨도다
out of the darkness
a great voice called to me and said
"나는 너를 왕위에 올렸던 주 너의 하나님이니라."
"I am the Lord thy God,
who placed thee upon the throne."
"그리고 나는 네게 선언하노라:
"And this I declare unto you:
"오직 화평만이 이스라엘의 부흥을 가능하게 할것이며, 다툼은 아니니라."
Only in peace can Israel prosper
and be made great, not in strife."
그리고 다시 주 여호와 하나님께서 그의 종 다비드에게 말씀하셨도다
And again, the Lord God Jehovah
spoke to his servant David:
"보아라, 너에게 태어난 아들, 화평의 사람이니라."
"Behold, a son has been born unto thee,
a man of peace."
"그래서 그를 솔로몬이라 이름하였노라."
"Wherefore,
thou hast named him Solomon."
"그리고 나는 영원히 그의 왕국을 건설할것이니라."
"And I will establish
his kingdom for ever."
- 왕국은 제것입니다!
- 하나님의 뜻은 그것이 아니다.
- The kingdom is mine!
- God wills it otherwise.
너는 그와 혼자 있는 시간을 잘 이용했구나.
You made good use
of your time alone with him.
너는 나에 대적하여 그의 쇠약함을 이용했다.
You used his weakness against me.
- 저는 이 일에 대해 아무것도 몰랐습니다.
- 거짓말하고 있군.
- I knew nothing of this.
- You lie.
- 너는 항상 말을 잘 지어냈어.
- 너는 그를 부당하게 핍박하고 있구나.
- You were always a weaver of words.
- You accuse him falsely.
당신이 나보다 그를 선택한 후에는?
저들도 선택을 해야 합니다.
After you've chosen him over me?
Theirs should be the choice.
- 그들이 선택하게 하라.
- 옳소, 우리 이야기도 들으시오.
- Let them choose.
- Aye, hear us.
- 아도니아.
- Adonijah.
- (crowd) Adonijah.
- 여러 장로들이여 무엇을 말할까?
- 하나님의 뜻을 받아들이시오
- You, the elders, what say you?
- Accept the will of God.
- 왕관은 나의것이다. 나는 그것을 위해 싸울것이오
- 아도니아는 정당한 상속자요.
- The crown is mine. I shall fight for it.
- Adonijah is the rightful heir.
폭력으로 인해 하나님의 분노가 임하지 않도록 행동하시오 .
Act not with violence
lest the wrath of God fall upon you.
나는 당신에게서 빼앗는 어떤 행동도 하지 않습니다
I have never done anything
to deprive you.
위선자의 입으로부터 나오는 말들이로다
Words from the mouth of a hypocrite.
아버지의 환심을 사기 위한 위선자의 행동이 아니냐?
Isn't yours the act of a hypocrite
in coming to greet your father?
당신은 다비드왕께서 살아 계신것을 알고 있음에도 불구하고
스스로 왕임을 선언했었오
You who proclaimed yourself king
even though you knew David lived.
헤즈라이의 말이 사실이냐?
Has Hezrai spoken truly?
나를 은밀히 감시하기 위해 그를 보냈다는것을 몰랐습니다.
I did not know that
you had sent him to spy on me.
내가 숨이 끊어질때까지 기다리지 못했느냐?
Could you not wait
until the breath left my body?
- 저는 기다리는것이 힘들었습니다.
- 왕은 법을 존중하고 지켜야 한다.
- I am weary with waiting.
- The king must respect and obey the law.
네 자신이 왕을 선포하는중에 하나님과 인간의 법을 범했도다
In proclaiming yourself,
you have violated the law of God and man.
오, 안돼
Oh, no.
나는 왕위가 내것임을 주장하며, 결코 그 권리를 포기하지 않을겁니다
I claimed what was mine by right,
and I shall never relinquish that right.
안돼
Oh, no.
솔로몬의 무능력을 발견하여 왕권을 취하는데 얼마나 걸릴까요?
How long will it take them
to discover his incompetence?
솔로몬 왕? 불가능해
Solomon king? Lmpossible.
지금 불법은 아도니아 자신의 입으로 밝혀졌다
Now it is revealed
out of the mouth of Adonijah himself
왜 하나님께서 그로부터 고개를 돌리셨는지
why God hath turned his face from him.
하나님의 지혜는 모든것을 알고 계십니다
The wisdom of God
passeth all understanding.
왜?
Why?
마치 이전에 있었던일이 쓰여 있는것처럼.
As it is written, so let it be done.
그것은 저의 죄입니다, 왜 절 치지 않습니까?
The sin was mine.
Why did you not strike me?
기혼의 물을 가져오라
Bring forth the waters of Gihon
그리고 여기 하나님의 명령으로
and here, as God commands,
난 경고했오, 솔로몬
하나님의 손이 당신위에 있오
I warned you, Solomon.
The hand of God is upon you.
이스라엘의 솔로몬 왕에게 기름을 부으라
anoint Solomon king of Israel.
- 하나님의 권능으로.
- By the grace of God.
- (elders) By the grace of God.
복종하라, 아도니아
하나님의 이름에 복종하고 무릎을 끓으라
Yield, Adonijah. Yield
and bend the knee in the name of God.
절대로
나의 상속권을 빼앗아간 이 아우보다는
Never! Rather would I
bend knee to the Pharaoh
차라리 파라오에게 무릎을 끓겠습니다
than to this brother
who has robbed me of my birthright!
그리고 하나님의 앞에 단일의 증표를 높이 들고
Then hold high the tablet of unity
before his eyes
하나님을 신성시하는 목적을 항상 기억해야 한다
so that he may ever remember
the purpose of his consecration.
(devotional singing in Hebrew)
솔로몬 만세
Hail Solomon,
하나님의 권능으로, 이스라엘의 왕이여
by the grace of God, king of Israel.
하나님의 권능으로, 이스라엘의 왕 솔로몬 만세
(all) Hail Solomon,
by the grace of God, king of Israel.
(murmured prayers)
네 형을 미워하지 말거라, 솔로몬
Turn not against thy brother, Solomon.
그의 혈기가 뜨겁지만 곧 식을것이다
His blood is hot, but it will cool.
맹세하겠습니다, 폐하
You have my pledge, sire.
그가 나의 형이란것을 절대 잊지 않겠습니다
I will never forget that he is my brother.
그리고 너, 애야, 왕가에 머물것이냐?
And you, my child,
will you remain in the king's household,
아니면 너의 아버지 아합과 함께 길레드로 돌아갈것이냐?
or will you return to Gilead
with your father Ahab?
폐하, 쉬셔야 합니다
Majesty, you must rest.
제가 다비드왕의 집에 오게 되었을때
나의 가족은 기쁨으로 노래불렀으며
When I was brought to the house of David,
my people sang songs of gladness,
난 쉴수 없다, 타칸
I cannot rest, Takyan.
저는 진심으로 즐거워 하였습니다
and I came with joy in my heart.
똑같이 저는 솔로몬의 집에 남을것입니다
With the same joy, I will remain
within the house of Solomon.
폐하께서 즉시 출발하실건지 폐하의 허락을 얻기 위해 왔습니다
I have come to ask your permission
to arrange your immediate departure.
내 마음에 무겁게 남아 있는것이 하나 있다
One thing remains heavy on my heart.
그래
Yes.
가자, 빨리
Let us go - quickly.
내가 젊엇을때, 나는 약속의 궤를 모셔둘
In my youth, I dreamed
that I would build a mighty temple
목적을 달성한 지금 우리가 남아있을 이유가 없다
There is no reason for us to remain now
that I have accomplished my purpose.
거대한 성전을 지을것을 꿈꾸었다
to house the Ark of the Covenant.
그러나 나는 큰 죄를 저질렀고
But I sinned greatly,
폐하께서는 자책하지 마십시오,
그것은 갑작스러운 폭풍이었을 뿐입니다
Your Majesty should not reproach herself.
It was nothing more than a sudden storm.
주님의 거소를 세우는데 적합하지 않았다
and was not fit to erect
the habitation of the Lord.
벼락에 죽는것은 처음 있는일도, 마지막도 아닙니다
It is not the first time lightning
has dealt death, nor will it be the last.
나의 맹세를 지켜다오, 나의 아들아
Redeem my vow, my son.
내가 꿈꾸었던 거대한 성전을 지을것을 약속해다오
Pledge me that you will build
the great temple of which I had dreamed
그것은 우연의 일치 이외에 아무것도 아니었을까?
Was it nothing more than a coincidence?
그래서 하나님께서 그의 백성들 가운데 거하실 거소를 가지시도록
so that God will have his dwelling place
among his people.
확실히 폐하께서는 이스라엘 사람들을 믿을수 없습니다
Surely Your Majesty
cannot believe the Israelites,
그것이 그들 신의 분노와 복수의 표시였을까요?
that it was a sign
of the anger and revenge of their god?
성전을 지을것을 약속드립니다
I promise you it shall be built.
강하고 훌륭한 용기가 있기를
Be strong and of good courage.
- 내가 무엇을 믿는지 더 이상 모르겠어
- 폐하, 과로하셨습니다
- I no longer know what I do believe.
- Majesty, you're overwrought.
그래요, 마지막 며칠동안의 긴장이 우리 모두에게 영향을 끼쳤습니다
Yes, the strain of the last few days
has affected us all.
두려워마라
Dread not,
또한 놀라지도 말아라
nor be dismayed.
그러나 이것은 폐하의 승리의 순간입니다.
파라오는 폐하의 승리에 기뻐할것입니다
But this is your hour of triumph.
The Pharaoh will rejoice in your victory.
시바는 폐하를 자랑스러워 할것입니다
Sheba can be proud of her queen.
내 자신이 매우 자랑스럽다
I am very proud of myself.
난 이집트로부터 보수를 받았다, 우린 홍해에 우리의 항구를 가질것이다
I have earned my reward from Egypt.
We will have our port on the Red Sea.
우리는 더 많은 금과, 더 많은 힘과, 더 많은 것들을 가질것이다
We will have more gold,
more power, more everything.
날 신뢰했던 위대한 남자를 배반한 댓가로
Because I have betrayed
a great man who trusted me,
모든것을 초월해 날 사랑했던 그를..
who loved me beyond all else.
시바인들이다. 시바인들이 오고있어요
The Sheban. The Sheban is coming.
오! 주여! 나의 하나님
O Lord, my God,
나의 아버지 다비드 대신에 이 종으로 왕을 삼으신 이여
thou hast made thy servant king
instead of David, my father,
저는 정말로 어린아이보다 나은것이 없습니다
and I am no more than a little child.
이 종에게 지혜로운 마음을 주소서
Give therefore unto thy servant
an understanding heart
여기에 시바인들이 오고 있어요
Here comes the Sheban.
백성들을 재판하여야 할지도 모르고
that I may judge thy people,
시바인들이에요
이리 오세요
- The Sheban.
- Come away.
선악을 분별해야 할지도 모릅니다
that I may discern between good and evil,
어느 누가 이렇게 많은 백성들을 재판 할수 있겠나이까?
for who is able to judge this,
thy so great a people?
페하를 중의회에 출두하시라는 것이 요청이 아니라는걸 아실겁니다
Your Majesty understands that it is not
a request that you attend the council.
그것은 각 지파 장로들의 명령입니다
It is a command
from the elders of the tribes.
네가 이것들을 구하였도다
(voice of God)
Because thou hast asked this thing
네 자신을 위하여 장수도 구하지 아니하며, 부귀도 구하지 아니하였으며
and hast not asked for thyself
long life, nor riches for thyself,
그들이 무엇을 말할지 모르지만, 피하고 싶지 않소
I have no wish to evade
what they have to say to me.
네 원수들의 생명 멸하기도 구하지 아니하였으나
nor the life of thine enemies,
오직 송사를 듣고 분별할 지혜를 구하였도다
but hast asked for understanding
to discern judgement.
보아라. 내가 네 말대로 하여
Behold, I have done
according to thy words.
내가 너에게 현명하고 지혜로운 마음을 주리라
I have given unto thee
a wise and understanding heart.
그리고 네가 나의 법규와 명령을 지켜
And if thou wilt walk in my ways,
나의 길로 행하면
keeping my statutes
and my commandments,
여기에 오는 위험을 감수해서는 안되오
You should not have taken the risk
of coming here.
만일 내가 지금 오지 않았더라면
If I had not come now,
부귀와 장수를 네게 주리라
I will give unto thee
both riches and honour
모든면에서 오는 용기를 잃어버릴지 몰라요
I might have lost
the courage to come at all.
그리하여 네 평생에 지상의 왕들 가운데
so there shall not be
among the kings of the earth
너와 같은 자가 없으리라
any like unto thee in all thy days.
한때, 당신은 제게 진실을 물었죠
Once, you asked me for truth.
그리고 전 사실대로 대답했어요, 그러나 전 당신을 속이기 위해 거짓말처럼 들리게 했어요
And I answered you with truth, but
I made it sound like a lie to deceive you.
파라오의 친구이며, 이스라엘의 적을 위해서 였어요
For I was a friend of the Pharaoh
and an enemy of Israel,
그리고 전 당신을 무너뜨리기 위한 증오로 여기에 왔어요
and I came here out of hatred
to destroy you.
- 할 가치가 없어
- 안돼요?
- Not good enough.
- No?
당신이 예루살렘에 도착했던 날 그것을 알았다오
Had I known this
the day you arrived in Jerusalem,
그것으로 바뀌는것은 아무것도 없오
it would have changed nothing.
(Joab laughs)
나의 죄는 더 크오
Mine is the greater guilt.
전하와 함께하면 종종 충분한 가치가 있죠.
내기를 두배로 하지요.
With you, I am seldom good enough.
Double the wager.
당신이 날 어디로 인도할것인지 처음부터 알았고 난 따라갔오
For I have known from the first
where you would lead, I would follow.
아주 좋아
Very well.
그가 왕으로 선택되었을때 나는 그를 죽여야 했다
I should have killed him
when he was chosen king.
참으십시오 전하, 기다리세요
Patience, Highness. Wait.
그러나 왜 해명할 필요없이 바로 가지 않았오?
But why did you not just go
without explanations?
- 나는 참을성이 강한 사람이 아니야
- 저도 알고 있습니다
- I am not a patient man.
- I am aware of that.
당신을 사랑하기 때문이에요
Because I love you.
내가 뭘 했는지, 모르겠어요
What I have done, I cannot undo.
무얼 하든지 함께 해요, 이것은 믿어주세요
Do with me what you will,
but this you must believe.
내 사랑은 거짓이 아니에요
My love is not a lie.
떠나자, 요압
Leave us, Joab.
폐하의 명령을 듣지 않았나? 요압
명령에 복종하라
Did you not hear His Majesty, Joab?
Obey his command.
이 땅을 놀라게 할 지혜를 가진 이여
For a man whose wisdom
is becoming the marvel of the land,
홀로 여기에 오는것에 두려움이 없구나
you show a surprising lack of it
by coming here alone.
저는 형님께 부탁을 하러 왔습니다
I have come to ask a favour of you.
내손이 이 창으로 너의 몸을 뜷고 싶어 한다는것을 아느냐?
Knowing that this hand of mine must ache
to drive this spear through your body?
자책으로 이스라엘의 분노를 달래려고 하지 마시오
Think not to appease the wrath of Israel
with remorse.
형님이 무슨 생각을 하고 있는지 알고 있습니다
I know what is in your heart.
하나님의 분노가 옆으로 돌려지지 않을거요
Neither will God's anger be turned aside.
내가 묻고 싶은 것은 형님이 나를 증오하는것 만큼 이 나라를 사랑하는냐입니다
All I ask is that you love your country
as much as you hate me.
난 변명하기 위한 어떤 말도 하지 않을것이오
I will speak no words in my defence.
당신의 잘못을 생각하여 무엇을 말할수 있오?
What could you say
in view of your transgressions?
애국심만 놓고보면 나는 이스라엘의 역사에서 가장 위대한 애국자가 될것이다
That would make me the greatest patriot
in the history of Israel.
당신으로 인해, 불화가 온땅을 채우고 있오
Because of you, dissension fills the land.
다윗께서는 제게 큰 부담을 주었습니다
David has laid a great burden upon me.
국가의 단일이 흩어지고 있오
The unity of the nation is sundered.
왕국을 다스리고, 성전을 건축하는 것 둘다 내가 맡은 일입니다
To rule the kingdom and to build the
temple, both of which I have undertaken.
그러나 형님은 군인과 지휘관으로서 탁월한 재능을 박탈당하고
But you have elected
to remain here in your lodge,
심지어 이것으로
Even as this,
단일의 상징이 산산이 부숴지는군
the symbol of its oneness,
is broken into fragments.
여기 자택에 머무는것을 선택하였습니다
depriving the people of your great talent
as a soldier and a commander.
단순히 건축하는것 만으로는 충분하지 않습니다
To build is not enough.
이 나라의 모든 적들로부터 방어할 무엇인가를 건축해야 합니다
What has been built must be defended
against all the enemies of the nation.
그 일에는 형님이 더 적합합니다
For that task,
you are far better suited than I.
예루살렘으로 돌아오십시오
Return to Jerusalem,
지파의 장로들은 당신이 왕임을 부인하고 떠나고 있오
The elders of the tribes deny you
as their king and depart from you.
제가 아니라, 이 나라와 하나님을 위하여 봉사해줄것을 요청합니다
offer your services, not to me,
but to your country and your God.
주 하나님께서는 당신을 먼지구덩이 속으로 내칠거요
The Lord God will smite you into the dust
너는 내가 군대를 통솔해 달라고 요청하느냐?
You are offering me
command of the army?
그리고 그의 백성들은 하나님의 이름을 찬양할거요
and his people will praise his name.
예
Yes.
내가 너를 대적하여 군대를 사용하려고 할지 모른다 해도？
Even though I might try
to use it against you?
그럴지어다
So be it.
예
Yes.
글쎄?
Well?
네가 현자중에 현자인지
아니면 바보중에 바보인지
I am trying to decide
if you are the wisest of the wise,
시험하고 있군
or the fool of fools.
그래서 솔로몬은 하나님의 길에서 행하였으며
So Solomon walked
in the way of his God,
그리고 긴 평화가 지속되는 동안, 이스라엘은 성장하고 발전하였다
and through a long era of peace,
Israel grew and prospered.
어리석음이 아주 높이 세워졌도다
Folly is set on great heights,
그리고 저것이 무너지듯이 어리석음으로 무너지리라
and that which has been done
is that which shall be done.
사람의 인생에서 무엇이 좋은지 누가 알겠는가?
Who knows
what is good for a man in his life,
그림자처럼 소모되는 그의 무익한 인생이?
his vain life
which he spends as a shadow?
헛되고 헛되니 모든것이 헛되도다
Vanity of vanities, all is vanity.
성전의 완공으로
With the completion of the temple,
솔로몬은 아버지에 대한 매우 신성한 맹세를 이행하였다
Solomon had fulfilled
a most sacred pledge to his father.
그러나 만일 나의 법규를 외면하고 저버리면
(voice of God) But if ye turn away
and forsake my statutes,
그때에는 내가 그들에게 주었던 나의 땅에서 그 뿌리를 뽑을것이요
then I will pluck them up by the roots
out of my land which I have given them,
그리고 높이 세운 이 집도
and this house which is high
그 집을 지나친 모든이들이 놀라 이렇게 말할것이다
shall be an astonishment to everyone
that passeth by it, so that he shall say
솔로몬. 이스라엘 위의 왕이시여
Solomon, king over Israel.
"왜 주께서는 이 땅과 이 집에 그리하셨느뇨?"
"Why hath the Lord done thus
unto this land and unto this house?"
그러면 이렇게 대답할것이니라 "그들이 그들을 이집트 땅에서 이끌어 낸
And it shall be answered "Because they
forsook the Lord God of their fathers
그들의 아버지 하나님을 저버렸으며,
which brought them forth
out of the land of Egypt
이스라엘의 주 하나님. 실로 그와 같은 신은 없도다
Lord God of Israel,
there is no god like thee.
다른 신들을 받들고, 참배하고,섬겼기 때문이라"
and laid hold on other gods
and worshipped them and served them."
하늘중의 하늘도 그를 품을수 없도다
Heaven of heavens cannot contain thee,
"그러므로 하나님께서는 그들 모두에게 이 악으로 갚으셨다"
"Therefore hath he brought
all this evil upon them."
그 이름을 위하여 지은 이 집이 어찌 이리 작은지요?
how much less this house
that I have builded unto thy name?
하지만 그 종과 그의 간구를 들으시고
Yet hear thy servant and his supplication,
장로들이 솔로몬을 비난하고 있습니다
The elders have denounced Solomon,
그리고 각지의 지도자들은 그들 자신의 터전으로 돌아갔습니다
and the captains of the host
have returned to their own provinces.
내 아버지 다윗에게 말씀하셨던 그말씀을 증거 하소소
and let thy word be verified
which thou spakest unto my father David.
공격 할 시간입니다. 폐하
This is the time to strike, Majesty.
온 이스라엘이 난리고 솔로몬은 고립됐습니다
All Israel is in turmoil,
and Solomon stands alone.
그리고 이스라엘 백성들이 이 장소를 향하여 기도할때
And of thy people Israel,
when they shall pray towards this place,
당신의 정보가 나보다 정확할것 같소
It seems that your information
is more accurate than mine.
하늘에서 들으시고 그들의 죄과를 용서하실때
hear thou in heaven,
and when thou hearest, forgive.
시바 여왕이 폐하께 이 상황에 대한 완전한 보고서를 주지 않았습니까?
Has not the Queen of Sheba
given you a full report on the situation?
이상하군, 여왕이 말하길 기다립시다
I have been wondering,
awaiting word from her.
이 집이 주의 것이듯 그들도 주의 백성이 되며
For they be thy people
as this house is thine,
폐하의 말씀은 내가 보고했던것이 아무것도 아니라고 그녀가 말했다는 겁니까?
You mean she has told you nothing
of what I have reported?
모든 땅이 주께서 하나님이신줄 알것입니다
that all the earth may know
the Lord is God.
아무것도
Nothing.
아마 그녀의 새로운 사랑으로, 폐하에 대한 의무를 잊은것 같군요
Perhaps in her new love,
she has forgotten her obligation to you
그 밖에 아무것도 없나이다
There is none else.
아멘
(all) Amen.
그녀가 좋아하는것 보다 솔로몬과의 동맹이 보입니다
and finds her alliance with Solomon
more to her liking.
당신은 내가 알아야 할 모든것을 말했소
You have told me
everything I should know,
당신의 아우에 대항하는 당신에 대한 나의 지원의 댓가를 제외하고
excepting your price for my support
of you against your brother.
시 바
전 이스라엘의 왕위를 원합니다, 그것은 항상 제것이었습니다
I want the crown of Israel.
It has always been mine.
자, 자
Come. Come.
그리고 솔로몬에 대적하여 폐하께서 보낸 군대의 지휘권도
And command of the army
that you send against Solomon.
자
Come...
오 폐하!
Oh, Majesty!
주겠소
I grant it.
그러나 당신에게 원하는게 한가지 있소
But there is one thing I want from you.
이리 와 우리와 합석하게, 바틀러
새에게 가르치고 있는중이야
Come and join us, Baltor.
I am teaching my bird to obey.
당신은 시바에 대한 나의 응징의 도구가 될것이오
You will be the instrument
of my punishment of Sheba
타칸은 반대지만. 난 동맹국이 필요해
Takyan disapproves. I need an ally.
그녀가 나를 배반한데 대해
for her betrayal of me.
틀림없이 파라오가 불평하고 있습니다
That is exactly what the Pharaoh
is complaining about.
파라오가 불평을 한다고? 우리가 그에게 가르쳐 주어야겠군
The Pharaoh is complaining?
We will have to teach him.
물론입니다. 폐하. 기대하셔도 됩니다
On that, Majesty, you can rely.
다른 연락이 이집트로부터 막 도착했습니다
Another message
has just arrived from Egypt.
새로운 이스라엘의 왕 만세
Hail to the new king of Israel.
- 기다려
- 그러나 중대한 일입니다
- Let it wait.
- But it is a serious matter.
새로운 이스라엘의 왕 만세
Hail to the new king of Israel.
파라오가 모든 왕들의 회합을 요청했습니다
The Pharaoh has called a conference
of all the kings.
앉게, 바틀러, 그대는 토키를 불안하게 하고 있어
Sit down, Baltor.
You make Tokki nervous.
농도를 더 짙게, 타칸
A deeper shade, Takyan.
석류빛깔, 그 색이야
Pomegranate. That is the right colour.
당신의 아우에게 그런 강한 군대가 있소？
Can your brother equal such strength?
글쎄, 바틀러?
Well, Baltor?
그는 소수의 추종자들만을 모을 수 있을것이오．
He will be able to gather
only a handful of followers.
이 시간에 무슨 일인가?
What is the problem this time?
폐하, 문제는 이스라엘 사람들입니다
Your Majesty,
the problem is the Israelites.
우리들은 빨리 칠것이오．승리는 결정된것이나 다름없오
We will strike quickly.
The victory must be decisive.
그들은 평화를 내세우면서도 군대를 강화시키고 있습니다
무슨 목적을 위해서죠?
They proclaim peace yet strengthen
their army, and for what purpose?
아마 그들은 파라오를 두려워 하고 있을거야
They are afraid of the Pharaoh, perhaps.
무엇이 두렵지?
What have we to fear?
영원한 증오에 불구하고
우린 지금 이스라엘과 우호적인 관계를 가지고 있다
In spite of our eternal hatred,
we now have friendly relations with Israel.
그들의 수는 얼마나 되느냐?
How many do they number?
천명 정도입니다
Thousands.
사실입니다만 우리는 안전을 위협받고 있습니다
True, but our security is threatened.
- 너는 그들이 국경에 교차하는것을 보았느냐?
- 예, 폐하
- You saw them cross over the border?
- Yes, Majesty.
거의 열광적으로 이스라엘인들은 그들의
위대한 왕 솔로몬을 지지합니다
Almost fanatically
they support their great King Solomon.
지평선에서 지평선까지 종렬해 있습니다
A column from horizon to horizon.
꿈꾸는자, 화평의 사람이라
A dreamer. A man of peace.
그러나 유일사상을 가진자가 사상이 많은 사람들 보다 더 위험하지요
But a man of ideas, and there is nothing
more dangerous than a man with an idea.
과연 예상대로군
It was to be expected eventually.
- 그 위협이 사실이냐?
- 매우 사실입니다.
- The threat is real?
- Very real.
우리들은 나가서 이집트인들과 마주칠것이다
We'll go out and face the Egyptians.
솔로몬의 위협은 단지 그의 군대가 아니라 그의 신에 있습니다
Solomon's threat
is not only his army, but his god.
명령을 내리라, 요시아
Give the orders, Josiah.
그의 신? 우리는 백명의 신이 있다
His god? We have a hundred gods.
할수 있을만큼 군대를 모아라
Gather what forces you can.
이 신은 모든 사람이 동등하며 이무도 노예가 아니라고 가르치는 유일신입니다
This is one god who teaches that
all men are equal and none are slaves.
예, 폐하
Yes, sire.
어리석은 생각이로군
What a foolish idea.
그렇지만.....만일 백성들을 사로잡은 사상이라면
And yet... if that idea
were to take hold of the people,
시바의 여왕은 곧 왕위에서 무너져 내릴것이다
the Queen of Sheba would soon
come crashing down from her throne.
이것으로 이집트 약탈자들의 무리를 저지하길 바랍니까?
With these
we hope to stem the Egyptian horde?
모든 다른 절대군주들이 그랬던 것처럼
As would all other absolute monarchs.
내 아버지 다비드께서는 돌과 양치는 막대기를 가지고 골리앗과 마주했다
My father David faced Goliath
with a stone and a shepherd's sling.
그러니까 이 회의에 참석하는 여러 왕들께 강력히 권고합시다
Therefore I strongly advise
Your Majesty to attend this conference.
하나님께서 다비드와 함께 계셨습니다
God was with David.
-용서 하십시오, 폐하
-용서할게 있느냐
- Forgive me, sire.
- There is nothing to forgive.
알고 있나? 바틀러
새를 잡으려면 먼저 덫에 미끼를 달아라
You see, Baltor?
To catch the bird, first bait the trap.
모든 이스라엘이 하나님께서 다비드의 아들을 버리셨다는 것을 안다
All Israel knows
that God has abandoned the son of David.
아마 우리는 파라오가 솔로몬의 문제를 해결하는것을 도울수 있을거야
Perhaps we can help the Pharaoh
solve the problem of Solomon,
일석이조이지
and kill two birds with one stone.
폐하, 작별인사 없이 그를 가게 하세요
Majesty, you let him go
without a word of farewell.
솔로몬이 이스라엘의 왕좌에 있은 이후
그가 강성해지는 것을 보았소
Since Solomon came to the throne of
Israel, I've watched his strength grow
내가 그에게 무슨 말을 할수 있을까?
What could I have said to him?
지금까지 그의 힘은 우리 국경에 위협이 되어 왔소
until now his power
has become a threat to my borders.
아이를 임신하고 있다고 그에게 어떻게 말할수 있을까?
How could I have told him
that I carry his child?
그리고 우리의 부와 무역이 그에게로 가는것이 보입니다
And the wealth and trade which once
came to us now finds its way to him.
또한 긴 시간 동안 우리들은 그의 파괴의 계획들을 늦췄소
For too long we have delayed
plans for his destruction.
예, 그에 대항하여 무기를 듭시다
강력한 군세를 일으킵시다
- Yes, take up arms against him.
- Raise a great host.
이스라엘을 먼지속으로 짓밟자
에글론 왕
- Trample Israel into the dust.
- King Eglon.
- 정지!
- Halt!
모압으로부터 나는 1,000대의 전차를 원하오
2,000대를 보내겠소
- From Moab, I want 1,000 chariots.
- I will send you 2,000.
칼두，칼데아는 나에게 5,000명의 궁술가들을 보내주시오
Kaldu, from Chaldea
you will send me 5,000 archers.
- 필요하다면 더.
- 내가 계획을 세운대로 정확하게 우리들은 공격할것이오.
- More if they are needed.
- We will attack exactly as I have planned.
동시에 북쪽, 동쪽과 남쪽에서 불시에 공격하면
From the north, the east and the south,
at the same time, by surprise.
- 전하, 적이 발견됐습니다
- 얼마나 떨어져 있나?
- Highness, the enemy has been sighted.
- At what distance?
그들은 어떻게 어디서 방어를 해야 할것인지 모를것이오
They will not know
how or where to make a defence.
행군으로 한시간 거리입니다
Within one hour's march.
우리들은 그들을 바다에 몰아 넣을것이오
그리고, 시바여
- We will drive them into the sea.
- And Sheba.
저들은 새벽까지 10리그를 이동했고, 우린 1리그를 이동했다
Then they have travelled ten leagues
since dawn and we have travelled one.
솔로몬에 대적하여 무슨 힘을 보낼거요?
What force will you send
against Solomon?
그들은 약하고 지쳤지만 우리는 아직도 건재하다
They are spent and exhausted
and we are still fresh.
아무것도
None.
태양이 떠오르기 2시간 전이다
Two hours yet before the sun sets.
왜? 당신은 우리 동맹이 아니오?
Why? Are you not my ally?
- 병사들을 배치하라
- 명령하십시오
- Deploy your men.
- Give the order.
모든 병사들과 말과 전차들을 솔로몬의 시야에서 숨겨라
We want every man, horse, chariot,
hidden from Solomon's view.
우리는 유일신의 위험한 사상을 가지고
있는 이스라엘을 멸망시켜야 하오
We must put an end to Israel, and with it
this dangerous idea of one god.
당신은 전쟁에 대해 말하지만.
사상과 신념을 어떻게 부술수 있나요?
You talk of war. How can you
destroy an idea, a faith,
그가 덫에 걸리면 모든 방위에서 그를 공격할것이다
When he rides into the trap,
our attack will hit him from every quarter.
지금 공격대형으로!
Now deploy for attack!
당신의 창 끝으로?
with the point of your spears?
공격 대형으로!
Deploy for attack!
그것이 이루어지려면 한가지 방법밖에 없어요
There is only one way it can be done.
위치를 잡아라. 공격대형으로!
Take your positions. Deploy for attack!
그것이 뭐요?
계획이 있소?
What do you suggest? Have you a plan?
있어요
I have.
그러나 모든 계획에는 대가가 있죠
But for every plan, there is a price.
이번에 무엇을 원하오?
What do you want this time?
솔로몬의 낙하의 답례로 홍해에 있는 멜리사항을 원해요
The port of Melish on the Red Sea
in return for the downfall of Solomon.
그것은 불가능하오
멜리사는 내 항구요
- That is impossible.
- Melish is my port.
시바, 이번엔 아주 많은것을 요구하는군
This time you ask for too much, Sheba.
말해봐요. 이스라엘과 싸움의 댓가가 무엇이죠?
Tell me, what would be
the cost of a war against Israel?
폐하, 우리 군사들은 지쳤습니다, 쉬어야 되지 않을까요?
Sire, our men are spent.
Shall we call a rest?
살라다르의 언덕에서 쉴것이오
They will rest at the dunes of Saladar.
거기에서 우린 참호를 파고 적을 기다릴것이오
There we will entrench
and await the enemy.
당신이 더 잘 알고 있잖소
You know very well.
그러면 당신이 거의 비용이 안드는 계획을 말해 보세요
And I offer you a plan almost without cost.
할수만 있다면 예루살렘에서 멀리 떨어져서 전투가 이루어지도록 합시다
Let the battle be joined
as far from Jerusalem as possible.
바틀러, 페하께서 주저하신다
His Majesty hesitates, Baltor.
폐하, 보십시오, 언덕위에 군사들입니다
Sire. Look, men on the hill.
우리들은 아마 예루살렘을 방문하는것 보다 오히려 시바로 돌아가야 할것 같다
Perhaps we should return to Sheba
rather than to visit Jerusalem.
- 행렬을 저지하라
- 정지!
- Halt the column.
- Halt!
기다리시오
Wait.
멜리사항을 주겠소
I grant it.
수넴사람들입니다!
Shunammites!
그럼 어떻게 솔로몬을 무너뜨릴것이오?
솔로몬은 현명한자라는데
- And how will you destroy Solomon?
- It is said that Solomon is wise.
그들은 우정의 깃발을 가지고 있군요
They bear a flag of friendship.
현명한 사람도 아무 문제 없어요
But no matter how wise a man may be,
그는 인간의 나약함을 가진 인간일뿐이죠
he is still human, with a human weakness.
아합!
Ahab!
우린 왕과 함께 하기 위해 왔습니다
We come to stand with the king.
나는 예루살렘에서 무리짓는 현자들처럼 솔로몬의 발치에 앉을거예요
I will sit at the feet of Solomon
like the wise men who flock to Jerusalem.
어찌하여 당신은 이 암울한 때에 나를 지원해 주는거요？
Why do you offer me your support
in this dark hour?
이집트인들에 대한 증오가 나에 대한 증오보다 큰거요？
Is your hatred for the Egyptians
greater than your hatred for me?
그리고 아마도 그의 입술로부터 그를 무너뜨릴 방법을 배우게 되겠죠
And perhaps I will learn
from his own lips the way to destroy him.
우리는 내딸 아비삭이 당신에게 주었던 사랑의 추억으로 왔습니다
We come in memory of the love
my daughter Abishag gave to you.
- 앞으로 우린 그 추억에 경의를 표할것이오
- 하나님의 의지로
- Then we will honour that memory.
- God willing.
정말로 여자의 방법이 우리 상식을 넘어서 있도다
Truly, the way of a woman
is beyond our understanding.
뒤로 가라
Fall in behind.
- 요시아
- 속보로 전진하라
- Josiah.
- Forward at the trot.
여자의 방법은 간단하지요, 맹주시여
The way of a woman is simple, my lord.
전진하라!
Forward!
그것은 항상 남자의 길을 따르는 것이죠
It is always to follow
the way of a man.
예루살렘에서 당신의 진행상황을 알려주도록 하시오
I shall keep myself informed
of your progress in Jerusalem.
(flutes and drums)
어머니! 오세요! 봐요! 어머니!
Mother! Come! Look! Mother!
공격을 시작하라
Start the attack.
공격!
Attack! Attack!
(bells)
원진을 이루라
Form a circle.
정지!
Halt!
영광입니다. 저는 베나이아로, 예루살렘까지 호위해 드리겠습니다
My compliments. I am Benaiah,
sent to escort you into Jerusalem.
환영합니다
시바 여왕폐하
Greetings.
Her Majesty the Queen of Sheba.
폐하! 이스라엘 왕께서 안부를 전하셨습니다
Your Majesty, the king of Israel wishes
me to convey his greetings to you.
정말 당신의 왕께서는 고상하신분 이시군요
Truly, your king has built nobly.
심지어 이집트도 이렇게 호화롭지 않아요
There is no such splendour,
even in Egypt.
폐하, 폐하의 형은 폐하께 대적하여 이집트인들과 힘을 합쳤습니다
Sire, your brother has joined forces
with the Egyptians against you.
전진하라, 전진하라, 더 빨리
Break through. Break through. Faster.
그리고 보이지 않는 신을 위한 모든것 조차도
And all that for a god he cannot even see.
앞으로
Forward.
이집트인들에게 기수들과 함께 전진하라고 전하라
Tell the Egyptians
to break through with their horsemen.
(fanfare)
- 원진을 부숴라
- 돌격하라
- Break the circle.
- Charge!
우리가 들었던 대로 그녀가 아름다울것으로 생각하나요?
Do you think she will be
as beautiful as we have heard?
이스라엘에 의해 환영받는 이교도는 내가 결코 보고 싶지 않은것이야
This is something I never thought to see,
a pagan welcomed to Israel.
그녀가 하나님을 알고 있지 않는한 어떻게 진실하신 하나님께 변화 될수 있겠소?
How can a pagan be converted
to the true God unless she knows him?
우리는 그녀가 이집트의 동맹국이라는것을 결코 잊어서는 안됩니다
We must never forget
she is an ally of Egypt.
그녀가 이집트의 동맹국이기 때문에
우리들은 그녀에게 우리 단일과 강함을 보여주어야 하오
Because she is an ally of Egypt, we must
show her our unity and our strength.
우리들의 적을 하나라도 더 줄이기 위해
그녀에게 친선을 요청합시다．
Let us offer her our friendship
in the hope that we have one less enemy.
퇴각신호를 울려라
Sound the retreat.
요압, 솔로몬을 찾아라
Joab, find Solomon.
매우 아름답군요, 그렇지 않나요?
She is very beautiful, isn't she?
폐하
Your Royal Majesty.
우리 군주이신 시바의 여왕폐하를 소개합니다
Permit me to present my sovereign,
Her Royal Majesty, the Queen of Sheba.
이스라엘은 페하를 열렬히 환영하오
Israel extends a warm welcome
to Your Majesty.
당신의 아름다운 나라를 방문하게 허가해 주셔서 감사드려요
I am grateful for your permission
to visit your beautiful country.
매우 긴 여행 후라 당신의 목적지에 도착해 기쁠것이오．
After so much travelling, you must be
pleased to have reached your destination.
만일 10시간 정도만 여행했다면 내가 본 경이로움으로
If I had travelled ten times the distance
it would be forgotten
저쪽으로 가자
Let's try over there.
잊어버릴만한 거리일거에요
in the face of the marvels I have seen,
당신의 도시인 예루살렘의 찬란함으로
and in the splendour
of your city of Jerusalem.
여왕이 바란다면 환영행사를 취소하고 쉬게 하겠소
If it pleases you, we can dispense
with ceremony and let you rest.
전하, 솔로몬의 방패를 발견했지만 솔로몬을 찾지 못했습니다
Your Highness, we found Solomon's
shield but so far not Solomon.
페하께서는 매우 사려가 깊군요
You are most considerate.
그러나 먼저 입구에서 낯선이에게 보여주었던 친절을 위하여
But first, let me offer
a token of my appreciation
평가의 댓가를 보여주도록 허락해주세요
for the kindness you have shown
to a stranger within your gates.
그는 오합지졸들과 함께 숨기위해 기어가고 있을것이다
He must have crawled off
to hide with his rabble.
아침에 우린 그들의 피신처에서 그들을 파헤칠것이다
In the morning,
we will dig them out of their burrows.
바틀러
하란!
- Baltor.
- Haran!
토끼사냥보다 더 중요한 일이 있다
I have more important things
than to occupy myself with a rabbit hunt.
계속 수색하라
솔로몬의 머리를 가져오는자에게는 금을 주겠다
Keep searching. There'll be gold for the
man who brings me the head of Solomon.
난 몹시 예루살렘에 들어가고 싶어
느린 군대때문에 늦쳐지고 싶지 않아
I'm impatient to enter Jerusalem. I do
not wish to be delayed by a slow army.
솔로몬의 저항을 부수는건 아무 문제 없을 것이다
You will have no trouble
in destroying Solomon's resistance.
그들을 정복했을때 예루살렘에 전속력으로 날 따라 오도록 하라
When you have vanquished them,
follow me into Jerusalem with all speed.
예루살렘에 들어가는데 군사가 얼마나 필요합니까?
How many men will you need to enter?
적은 호위만, 거기서 아무 저항없이 만날것이다
Only a small escort.
I will meet with no resistance there.
명령대로 하겠습니다
Your commands will be obeyed.
하씬 지휘관은 여섯명의 관리를 데리고 폐하와 함께 예루살렘으로 갈것입니다
Colonel Hassin with six officers
will go with His Majesty to Jerusalem.
너무 많은 선물이에요
그렇소, 아주 멀리서 가져왔소
- So many gifts.
- Yes, and brought from so far.
내일 우리들중 아도니아와 그의 이집트인들과 마주칠수 있는자는 얼마 되지 않을것이다
There'll be few of us left to face Adonijah
and his Egyptians by tomorrow.
그런 부들이!
Such riches.
겁쟁이들이 어둠에서 우릴 버리고 있습니다
The faint-hearted are deserting us
in the darkness.
그들을 나무랄수 있나, 요시아
Can you blame them, Josiah,
심지어 내 형까지 날 대적하여 돌아선 마당에?
after they have seen
even my own brother turn against me?
난 그가 야심을 추진할 열정이 있다고 생각했다
I thought I knew
the driving passion of his ambitions,
그러나 백성들을 배반하리라고는 결코 생각하지 못했다
but never did I think
he would betray his own people.
나의 감사와 내 백성들의 고마움을 표현할 적절한 말이 없군요
I have no adequate words to express
my thanks and the gratitude of my people.
(footsteps)
이날이 이스라엘과 시바사이에
Along with them, I offer my hand
우린 단지 약간의 우리 백성들의 흩어진 부대를 발견했을뿐입니다
We only found
a few scattered units of our people,
국교의 시작임을 나타내기 희망하여 내 백성들과
in the hope that this day will mark
the beginning of a closer friendship
심지어는 거의 모두가 어둠속에서 그들을 보는것을 두려워하고 있습니다
almost afraid to show themselves
even in the darkness.
나의 수고를 제공하지요
between Israel and Sheba.
그것은 모든것중에 가장 환영할 선물입니다
That would be
the most welcome gift of all.
아침에, 이집트인들은 우릴 누르고 예루살렘에서 행진할것입니다
In the morning, the Egyptians
will march over us into Jerusalem.
우리가 얼마나 남든지, 우린 싸울것이다
No matter how few of us are left,
we will fight on.
만약 내가 명예로운 왕으로서 살아갈수 없다면,
If I cannot live as a king with honour,
최소한 난 명예로운 왕으로서 죽을수 있오
at least I can die as a king with honour.
(wailing)
비통하도다! 우리 왕이 패하였도다!
Woe unto us! Our king is defeated!
폐하
Majesty.
비통한 절규가 솔로몬 군대의 탈주병들에게 돌고 있습니다
The outcry is over the news brought
by deserters from Solomon's army.
그는 패한것 같습니다. 그의 부하들이 패주했습니다
It seems he has been defeated,
his men routed.
베나이아, 당신은 시바인들의 땅이 항상 이럴것으로 생각하나요?
Benaiah, do you suppose the land
of the Shebans is always like this?
예, 그렇게 생각됩니다
I would think so, yes.
그는.......죽었나요?
Is he... among the dead?
아무도 모릅니다.
그러나 아침에는 모두 그렇게 말했습니다
No one knows,
but all say that by morning,
단 한명의 이스라엘 사람도 살아 돌아가지 않을겁니다
not one Israelite will escape alive.
지금 폐하께서는 안전하십니까? 이스라엘 사람들은 페하를 비난할 겁니다
Now will Your Majesty seek safety?
The Israelites will blame you.
난 폐하께서 다시 거절하지 않기를 바래요,
폐하는 자신을 지켜야 해요
I beg Your Majesty, do not refuse again.
You must save yourself.
여왕이 기다리게 해서는 안됩니다
We must not keep the queen waiting.
- 폐하, 어디로 가십니까?
- 날 붙들지 말라, 바틀러
- Majesty, where are you going?
- Do not try to stop me, Baltor.
거리에 들어가 위험하게 할순 없습니다
I will not let you take the risk
of going into the streets.
비켜라!
Stand aside!
(gong)
어서 오시오
Welcome.
둘에게 명령한다.
날 따라오지 말라
I command you both,
do not follow after me.
여왕을 위한 소식이오
A message for your queen.
솔로몬은 패배했다. 권능이 떨어졌도다
(man) Solomon is vanquished!
How are the mighty fallen.
여왕폐하이십니다
Her Majesty the Queen.
솔로몬 국왕폐하의 안부 인사를 전해드립니다
비통하도다! 이집트인들이 우릴 지배할것이다
His Majesty King Solomon
sends his greetings
(man #2) Woe unto us.
The Egyptians will be upon us.
그리고 제게...우리들에게 명령했습니다
and has commanded me -
has commanded us -
그의 죄로 인하여 주께서 솔로몬을 징벌하셨도다
(man #3) The Lord
has punished Solomon for his sins.
폐하의 요청에 대한 답변을 알려 드립니다
to inform Your Majesty that in response
to Your Majesty's request
누가 파라오로부터 우리를 지켜 줄것인가?
Who will save us now from Pharaoh?
개인 접견으로 폐하를 맞이하는것이 가장 행복 할것이라 하셨습니다
he will be most happy
to receive you in private audience.
우리의 죄악이 이를 초래하였도다
(man #4) Our sins
have brought this upon us.
그는 아주 정중하시군요
He is most gracious.
비통하도다, 이집트인들이 우리의 고귀한 솔로몬을 전복하였도다
Woe unto us. The Egyptians
have overthrown our noble Solomon.
이렇게 근사한 사절을 보내다니, 얼마나 사려 깊으신 왕인가!
How thoughtful of the king
to send so charming an envoy.
왕께서는 제가 여기 있는것을 모른답니다
He doesn't know I'm here.
파라오는 우리 모두를 죽일것이오
Pharaoh will slay us all.
제가 여기에 오기를 열망했지요
I was so anxious to come.
더욱 기쁘네요
들어 오세요
Then I am even more pleased. Come in.
솔로몬은 하나님의 길을 따르지 않았오
(man #5) Solomon did not follow
the path of God.
그대는 폐하의 궁정에서 나를 처음으로 방문하는거에요
You are the first of His Majesty's court
to visit me.
야영이 얼마나 재미 있나요?
How interesting your encampment is.
폐하의 백성들은 항상 근심이 없고 명랑한가요?
Are your people
always so carefree and gay?
우리는 인생과 기쁨을 즐겨요
We enjoy life and pleasure.
- 그래요?
- 그래요
- Don't you?
- Yes, we do.
그러나 우리는 금욕적인 사람들이에요
우린 좀 더 진지해지길 바라죠
But we are an austere people.
We tend to be more serious.
그럼 당신의 왕, 그도 마찬가지로 진지한가요?
And your king. Is he also serious?
이스라엘의 하나님이시여
God of Israel,
전지전능하신 이여
thou who art called
the all-knowing, the compassionate,
솔로몬 왕은 큰 책임이 있어요
King Solomon has a great responsibility.
그는 12지파의 단일을 유지해야 하죠
He must maintain
the unity of our 12 tribes.
내 마음을 살피시고 내 기도를 들으소서
look into my heart and hear my prayer.
당신과 당신의 백성들을 거스리는 나의 죄를 용서하소서
Forgive my sin against thee
and thy people.
그렇게 중요한가요? 이 단일이?
It is very important, this unity?
물론이죠
단일 없이는 이스라엘은 없을거에요
Oh, yes. Without it,
there would be no Israel.
제게 솔로몬의 생명을 맡기면 그의 적으로부터 그를 보호하겠나이다
Grant me the life of Solomon
and preserve him against his enemies.
그렇게 하시면, 전 시바로 돌아가 그릇된 신들을 몰아 내겠나이다
Do this, and I will return to the land
of Sheba and cast down the false gods.
시바의 신들이에요, 말라, 운명의 보호자
The gods of Sheba.
Mal-Ra, the guardian of destiny.
그리고 당신 이름의 영광을 위하여 성전을 지으며
And I will build a tabernacle
to the glory of thy name,
콜, 태양과 별들의 신
Kol, god of the sun and stars.
비를 보내는 라마
Rama, who sends the rain.
당신 앞에 그 어떤 신도 두지 않겠나이다
and there shall be
no other gods before thee.
우리는 많은 신들을 가지고 있어요
We have many gods.
이스라엘에서는 신은 하나에요
In Israel, we have one god.
신이 당신을 실망시키면 그대는 모든것으로 신을 비난하나요?
When he fails you,
do you blame him for everything?
신께서는 결코 우리 기대를 저버리지 않아요
He never fails us.
그대는 왕의 근처에만 있어서 만족하고 있나 보네요
You must find it gratifying
to be so close to your king.
그대는 아마 그의 여동생이겠죠?
Are you his sister, perhaps?
때론 왕은 저를 부르죠, 우리는 서로 매우 가까워요
Sometimes he calls me that.
We have been very close to each other,
내가 그의 아버지의 집에 살기 위해 온 후로는요
ever since I came to live
in the house of his father.
이스라엘에 오래 머무르실 건가요?
Do you stay long in Israel?
그대의 왕에게 달렸어요
That depends upon your king.
그대는 매우 근사하고 순진해 보이는군요
요시아
You are charming. Innocent.
Josiah.
- 폐하, 무엇때문에 놀라십니까?
- 놀란게 아니라 희망이네
- What has alarmed you, sire?
- Not alarm, but hope.
그대 또한 뜻대로 이룰거에요
And you fulfil all my expectations.
어둠 가운데 빛처럼 다가오는 희망이야
Hope that comes like a light
in the midst of darkness.
마치 하나님께서 내게 오셔서 길을 보여 주시는것 처럼
It is as though God had come to me
and showed me the way.
그대를 위하여
For you.
시바의 땅으로부터
From the land of Sheba.
그 여왕으로부터의 선물이에요
A gift from its queen.
예?
Yes?
폐하
Sire.
이, 솔로몬, 전능자여
This Solomon the Almighty...
- 회군한다
- 그리고 저길봐!
- Our men return.
- And there.
무슨 놈의, 전능자?
Almighty what?
그와 개인접견을 할떄에는 20명의 사람이 둘러싸고 있어
20 men surrounding him,
and he calls it a private audience.
그는 국왕으로서 폐하를 즐겁게 했습니다
그리고 그 만찬회들도요
- He has entertained you royally...
- And those state banquets!
나는 한쪽 끝에 있고 그는 다른 쪽에 있다
I at one end, he at the other.
저길봐!
And there!
그리고 우리 사이에 음산한 얼굴의 노인들....
And in between us,
a lot of sour-faced old men.
한번도 혼자 그와 함께 있은적이 없어, 한번도
Not once have I been with him alone.
Not once.
그러나 우리는 여기에 5일밖에 있을수 없습니다
But we have only been here five days.
이 솔로몬은 이집트의 파라오보다도 더 접근하기가 어렵워
This Solomon is more difficult to
approach than the Pharaoh of Egypt.
이 위대한 왕은 한 사람의 남자로서의 시간을 제외하고
모든 시간이 사람들을 위한거야
This great king has time for everything,
except the time for being a man.
몇백의 병사들이 재집결하고 있다
They rally to us, by the hundreds.
사랑의 신 라곤이여, 그를 나에게 보내주세요
Send him to me, Rha-Gon, god of love.
나를 여자들중 가장 매혹적으로 만들어 주세요
Make me the most desirable of women.
내 입술로 꿀처럼 달콤하게, 나의 피부는
Make my lips sweet as honey,
그들의 방패를 닦게하라, 거울처럼 비치도록
Set them to burnishing their shields.
Let them shine like mirrors.
부드럽고 꽃잎처럼 향기롭게 만들어 주세요
my skin soft and fragrant
like the petals of a flower.
예, 폐하
Yes, sire.
그를 나에게 주세요
Give him to me.
내 발치에 그를 원합니다
I want him at my feet.
(gong)
폐하께, 왕족의 방문객이 있습니다
(Takyan) Your Majesty has a royal visitor.
한때 그대가 내게 강의한것이 기억나오, 헤즈라이
이스라엘의 왕위에 오르는법에 대해서.....
I remember you once lectured me, Hezrai,
on how a king of Israel is crowned.
여왕폐하와 저는 전에 만난적이 있지요
Her Majesty and I have met before.
이 왕좌에 앉을 내 권리를 부정하는 당신에게 무슨 이유가 있오?
Are there any among you
who deny my right to sit upon this throne?
폐하께 사과드립니다
My apologies to Your Majesty.
당신을 영접하는 환영회가 불가능 했던것을 유감스럽게 생각합니다
I regret that I was unable
to be at the reception to welcome you.
환영회가 있었다면 나의 영접이 완벽해졌을텐데
Had you been there, it would have
made my welcome complete.
그때에는 내 왕위를 얻을 분별력 없는 의식 따윈 필요 없었어
Then I need no senseless ritual
to attend my elevation.
폐하께서는 겸손하시군요
오히려 마지막 방문할때와는 다르게
Your Majesty is gracious. Rather different
from the occasion of your last visit.
기혼의 물로 기름부음을 받는 따윈 필요없다구
No anointing with the waters of Gihon.
내가 올바르게 기억하고 있다면, 전하께서는 그때 왕이셨죠
If I remember rightly,
Your Highness was then a king.
항상 내 자리였던걸, 내손으로 얻었다
I take with my own hands
what has always been mine.
예, 그리고 왕으로서 파라오와 대적하는 동맹을 신청했지요
Yes. And as a king, I offered you
an alliance against the Pharaoh.
아도니아님 만세, 이스라엘의 사자여
Hail Adonijah, Lion of Israel.
그리고 내 답은 친절하지 않았어요
And my answer was not too kind.
아도니아님 만세
Hail Adonijah.
그래서 기억합니다
So I remember.
모두들, 이것을 알라
난 파라오와 동맹을 맺었다
Know this, all of you.
I have made an alliance with the Pharaoh.
난 이번에는 위험을 무릅쓰고 다른 동맹을 맺을것을 제안하오
This time I venture to offer you
another alliance.
그의 비호아래, 난 이스라엘을 지배할것이다
Under his protection, I will rule Israel,
당신은 이스라엘 왕의 사절로서 왔나요?
Do you come as envoy
from the king of Israel?
그리고 내게 반대하는 그 누구라도 자비를 베풀지 않을것이다
and I'll have no mercy
on any who oppose me.
나는 이스라엘 왕좌의 올바른 상속자인 아도니아로서 왔소
I come as Adonijah,
rightful heir to the throne of Israel.
폐하, 시바의 창녀가 발견되었습니다
Sire, the Sheban harlot has been found.
우리 동맹은 양쪽에서 원하는 많은것을 우리에게 줄수 있소
An alliance between us could give us
many things we both desire.
그녀는 성전으로 피난했습니다
She has taken refuge in the temple.
당신은 동생의 왕좌를 빼앗는데 우리 시바의 도움을 원하나요?
Do you want Sheban arms
to help you usurp your brother's throne?
솔로몬은 강탈자요
Solomon is the usurper.
내가 왕좌에 있으면 우리 영토는 이집트를 둘러쌀수 있었소
Once I am on the throne,
our lands could encircle Egypt,
그리고 모든 왕들은 우리의 자비를 구했을거요
and all of the kings
would be at our mercy.
왜 그들이 내게 자비를 구해야 하죠?
Why should I want them at my mercy?
나는 왕들과 좋은 관계를 유지하고 있어요
I maintain good relations with the kings.
그리고 솔로몬 왕은 나의 친구에요
And King Solomon is my friend.
- 정지!
- Halt!
그래서 어떻게 당신의 제의가 나를 흥미롭게 할수 있나요?
So how could your offer
possibly interest me?
날카롭게 우는 독수리가 구구대는 비둘기로 변했는가?
Has the screaming eagle
been transformed into a cooing dove?
사람들이 변하지 않으면 어떻게 세상이 답답할수 있나요?
How dull the world would be
if people never changed.
나는 더 현명해요, 아도니아 왕자
I am wiser, Prince Adonijah.
- 다시 이스라엘인들이..
- 어디서 그렇게 많은 군사들을 모았지?
- Again the Israelites.
- Where did they gather so many men?
난 더 이상 칼로 싸우지 않아요
I no longer do battle with a sword.
지난밤 오로지 죽은자 외엔 아무도 보지 못했습니다
Last night we could find none,
only their dead.
그것이 당신의 방문을 싫어하는 이유요
That's why I find your visit so disturbing.
몇분내로, 그들은 모두 죽을것이다
In a few minutes, they will all be dead.
나는 당신이 평화의 올리브 가지를
가지고 오는것을 믿기가 어렵소
I find it difficult to believe that you come
bearing an olive branch of peace.
오늘은 그들이 달아날 어둠이 없다
Today there is no darkness
into which they can escape.
내가 화평의 남자인 솔로몬 왕에게 그밖에 무엇을 가져올수 있는가?
What else could I bring to King Solomon,
who is a man of peace?
그들은 동쪽을 바라보고 있어 태양에 의해 보지 못할겁니다
They face east,
and will be blinded by the sun.
- 정면공격을 준비하라
- 정면공격
- Prepare for a frontal attack.
- Frontal attack.
폐하, 내가 내 시간뿐 아니라 폐하의 시간까지
낭비하고 있는것이 확실하군요
Your Majesty, it is clear
that I waste your time as well as mine.
폐하의 윤허로...
With Your Majesty's permission...
날카롭게 우는 독수리로서 당신을 더 좋게 이해했다고 생각해요
I think I understood you better
as the screaming eagle.
- 그들이 우릴 공격해오고 있습니다
- 내 신호를 기다려
- They are going to charge us.
- Wait for my signal.
그는 아직도 개자식이야
He is still a dog.
(shouted orders)
법정에 여자들이 앞으로 나오게 하시오
Let the women in judgement
come forward.
전에는 결코 법정에서 외국인은 왕 옆에 않지 못했소
Never before has an alien
sat beside our king in judgement.
공격, 그들을 쓰러뜨려라
Attack. Strike them down.
그녀의 존재가 모든 이스라엘을 더럽히는군
Her presence profanes all Israel.
공격하라!
Attack!
누가 불평하느냐?
Who makes complaint?
공격하라!
Charge!
나의 주 왕이시여, 이 여자 레아와 저는
같은집에서 살고 있었습니다
My Lord King, this woman Leah and I
dwell within the same house.
저는 아이를 출산했습니다
I was delivered of a child.
제가 아이를 낳고 난 3일후에 저 여자도 아이를 낳았습니다
On the third day after I was delivered,
she was delivered also.
집에는 아무도 없었고 우리 둘만 있었습니다
There was no one in the house
but we two.
밤중에 그녀가 옆으로 눕는 바람에 그녀의 아이가 죽었습니다
In the night, this woman's child died
because she lay upon it,
무슨 이유로 제가 잠들고 있는 사이에 내 옆에서 아이를 데려 갔으며
wherefore she removed my son
from beside me while I slept
내 가슴에 기대어 그녀의 죽은 아이를 눕혀 놓았습니다
and laid her dead child against my bosom.
- 거짓말입니다
- 조용히 하라
- She lies.
- (Solomon) Silence.
그리고 아침에 일어나 아이를 보살폈으나 그 애는 죽어 있었습니다
And when I rose in the morning
to nurse my child, he was dead.
- 아닙니다, 주 솔로몬이시여
- 사실입니다. 주 왕이시여
- Not so, Lord Solomon.
- The truth, Lord King.
내 팔에 안겨있는 아이를 보았을때
내가 낳았던 아들이 아니라는 것을 알았습니다
For when I looked at the child in my arms,
I knew it was not the son that I did bear.
- 그 애는 내 아들이 아니고 다른 애였습니다
- 살아있는 아이가 내 아들이다
- It was her own child and none other.
- The living child is mine.
- 죽은 애는 너의 아이야, 산 애가 내 아들이다
- 유아를 앞으로 데려오라
- The dead is yours, the living mine.
- Bring the infant forward.
요시아
Josiah.
폐하?
Sire?
내 앞의 계단에 아이를 올려 놓아 나로 그애를 보게 하라
Place the child on the steps before me
and show him to me.
- 지금!
- 방패 앞으로!
- Now!
- Shields forward.
요시아, 칼을 꺼내라
Draw your sword, Josiah.
아이를 두개로 쪼개라
Divide the child into two parts.
반은 한 여인에게 주고
반은 다른 여인에게 주어라
Give half to the one woman,
half to the other.
안되요!
No!
저 여자가 옳아요
If it must be,
아이를 죽이지 않을수 있다면 아이를 그녀에게 주세요
give the child to her
that it may not be slain.
나누세요
그애는 저 여자의 것도 나의것도 아니어야 합니다
Divide it.
It should be neither hers nor mine.
어머니여, 아이를 데려가라
그 애는 확실히 너의 아이다
Take your son, mother. He is surely yours.
주 하나님 여호와께서 왕을 칭찬하고 축복하기를
May the Lord God Jehovah
praise and bless you.
그대는 그 애가 해침을 당하는 것보다 오히려
다른 이에게 넘겨 주려고 했다
You would rather have surrendered him
to another than to see him harmed.
그리고 이 여인을 데려가서
And take this woman hence
위증에 대한 벌을 집행하라
and administer to her
punishment to fit her perjury.
거짓말입니다. 거짓말이에요
She lies. She lies.
그것은 거짓입니다. 아이는 제 아이입니다
It's not right. The child is mine.
제 아이에요!
Mine!
지금 마지막으로 저는 솔로몬 왕의 판결을 보았어요
Now, at last, I have seen
a judgement of Solomon,
그리고 당신의 지혜는 우리를 놀라게 했어요
and your wisdom amazes me.
무엇이든지 내게 주어졌던 지혜는 나의 백성들을 위한 것이오
Whatever wisdom has been given me,
it was for the benefit of my people.
계속 제게 가르쳐 주기를 청합니다
Continue to teach me, I beg of you,
그래서 제가 당신의 경이로운 이해심에서
더욱 큰 통찰력을 얻을수 있기를
so that I may gain a greater insight
into the wonder of your understanding.
그것은 내 백성들위에서 더욱 훌륭하고
현명한 지배자가 되는것이 가능하게 할것입니다
It will enable me to become a better
and wiser ruler over my own people.
진정한 지혜는 진실과 거짓가운데 분별할수 있게 하는데 있오
Real wisdom lies in the ability
to decide between the true and the false.
이스라엘의 주 하나님이시여, 승리는 주의 것이로다
Lord God of Israel,
thine is the victory.
주께서는 우리의 검이요, 방패시로다
Thou art our sword and our shield.
모든 군대들의 주 하나님이시여
Lord God of hosts.
당신께서는 주 하나님이시며, 이리 된것은 당신의 백성들을 사랑하셨기 때문이로다
Thou art the Lord God. What thou hast
done was out of love for thy people.
만일 내 마음을 살피신다면, 날 용서하소서
If thou knowest what is in my heart,
grant me forgiveness.
4년전에는 불모의 사막이었다는 것을 당신은 믿을수 있오?
Can you believe that only four years ago,
all this was barren desert?
아멘
Amen.
당신이 이룩했던 모든것에는 그런 즐거움이 있군요
You have such a joy
in all you have accomplished.
산에서 물을 가져와 사막에서 꽃이 피게 만드는것은 즐거운 일이오
It is a joy to make the desert bloom
by bringing water from the mountains.
아합, 요시아
Ahab. Josiah.
당신은 여기를 낙원으로 만들었군요
You have made this into a paradise.
20명의 병사를 택하고, 그들을 말에 태워라
Choose 20 men. Mount them on horses.
먼지로부터 이집트의 깃발을 모아라
Gather up the Egyptians' banners
from the dust.
내가 아니라 물, 일, 태양의 따사로움이 그 일을 했다오
The water, the work,
the warmth of the sun have done it, not I.
다비드의 도읍이 지켜질것을 선언하기 위해 그들과 함께 예루살렘에 갈것이다
We will ride with them to Jerusalem
to proclaim that the City of David is saved.
최근 수일간 나는 이스라엘의 많은것을 보여 주었오
In the last few days,
I have shown you much of Israel.
그러나 그대 나라의 어떤것도 내게 말하지 않는군
But you have not told me
anything of your own country.
지금까지, 솔로몬은 그 자신의 행위로 인해 죽었다
By now,
Solomon is dead by his own deeds.
이순간 내 나라의 땅은 별들처럼 멀게만 보이는군요
At this moment, my own land
seems as distant as the stars.
이집트의 검은 그를 심판했다
An Egyptian sword
has rendered judgement upon him.
누가 그대들을 굴복시키고 도읍을 파괴할 약탈자들을 막겠는가?
It is I, Adonijah, who has prevented
the hordes from falling upon you
청년기에，나는 지상의 모든 먼 곳의 왕국들을 방문하는 것을 꿈꾸곤 했오
In my youth, I used to dream of visiting
all the faraway kingdoms of the earth.
그것은 나, 아도니아다
and razing this city.
그런데 지금은 그대신 그 나라의 지배자들이 당신에게 오는군요
And now instead,
the rulers of those countries come to you.
- 아도니아님 만세, 이스라엘의 구세주여
- 아도니아님 만세
- Hail Adonijah, saviour of Israel.
- (sparsely) Hail Adonijah.
그대는 혼자서 시바를 다스리오
You rule Sheba alone.
처음부터 시바에서는 오직 여왕들만이 통치했어요
From the beginning of time,
only queens have ruled in Sheba.
모든 문제의 원인이 성전안에 있다
There in the temple
is the cause of all your troubles.
그것은 이스라엘에 불행을 몰고온 그녀다
It was she
who brought disaster upon Israel.
그것이 저희 법이에요
That is our law.
내 나라에 관해서 많은것들을 폐하께 말씀드리는 것이 기쁘군요
I would be happy to tell Your Majesty
many things concerning my country
- 그녀를 어떻게 하면 좋겠나?
- 개들에게 먹이시오
- What shall be done with her?
- Let the dogs devour her.
- 거리로 끌어내시오
- 그녀를 우리에게 주시오
- Drag her through the streets.
- Give her to us.
확신하노니, 그것은 페하께 중요한 일이에요
if I were sure it would be
of interest to you.
왜 그렇게 말하시오?
Why do you say that?
성전의 지성소를 더럽혀선 안되오
The sanctuary of the temple
must not be violated.
너무 늦게서야 당신을 방문했기 때문이죠
Because after all the times
I have visited you,
(murmuring)
폐하께서는 저의 야영지를 방문하는것으로 치하해 주지 않고 있군요
you have not returned the compliment
by visiting my encampment.
내가 지배하는 이스라엘에서는 이교도의 창녀를 위한 성역은 없다
In the Israel that I rule,
there is no sanctuary for a pagan harlot.
그리고 저 또한
And me.
그대들이 그녀를 심판하라
그대들에게 주겠다
You are her judges. I give her to you.
아마도 난 초대를 기다리고 있었을거요
Perhaps I was waiting for an invitation.
(murmuring)
오실것을 약속하나요?
You promise to accept?
약속하오
I promise.
마침내 폐하께서 방문한다니 정말 기쁘군요
I am so happy
that at last you have come to visit me.
내 백성들은 경의를 표할거에요
My people feel honoured.
경의를 표해야 하는것은 그대의 손님이라오
It is your guest who feels honoured.
유치한 오락에 지루하지는 않나요?
You are not bored
by our primitive pastimes?
아니오，당신을 즐겁게 하는 것을 배우는 것이 내게 흥미를 느끼게 하오
No, it interests me
to learn what amuses you.
됐어, 타칸
Enough, Takyan.
가게 해 주세요
Let me pass.
전에 한때는 내가 왕이었다고 말했고, 그대는 날 사깃군이라고 불렀지
Once before I told you I was king
and you called me an impostor.
만일 내가 저것을 막지 않으면
내 백성들은 계속 머물며 폐하를 꼼짝않고 바라볼텐데．
If I do not prevent it,
my people would stay and stare at you.
지금 내가 왕이라는걸 증명하겠다
Now I shall prove to you
that I am the king.
너에게 내 첫번째 재판의 명예를 주지
I grant you
the honour of my first judgement.
전설적인 솔로몬왕을...
Fabled Solomon.
돌을 던져라!
Stone her!
내가 당신을 꼼짝않고 바라보는 방법은?
The way I stare at you?
(gong)
지금은 라곤의 시간이에요
This is the hour of Rha-Gon.
매일밤 나는 그에게 공양하죠
Every evening, I make an offering to him.
- 말했다, 명령에 복종하라
- 돌을 던져라
- I have spoken. Obey my command.
- Stone her.
이교도의 허튼 계집을 죽여라
Kill the pagan slut.
라곤, 생명을 주시는 이여, 사랑의 신이여
Rha-Gon, giver of life, god of love,
나의 감사와 헌신의 증표를 받으소서
accept this token of my gratitude
and devotion.
솔로몬이다! 이겼다! 이겼다!
Solomon! Victory! Victory!
(gong)
라곤의 축제는 가장 신성한 의식이에요
The Feast of Rha-Gon
is the most sacred rite
시바의 땅에서는 매년 축하했지요
celebrated each year in the land of Sheba.
그러나 오늘밤은 신들의 이야기도 없을거에요
But tonight let there be no talk of gods.
이겼다! 승리했다! 솔로몬이 돌아온다
Victory! Victory! Solomon returns.
심지어는 지혜조차도
Not even of wisdom.
그리고 가슴을 따뜻하게 하는 시바의 포도주가 있지요
And there is Sheban wine
to warm the heart.
당신께 드립니다
My offering to you.
- 이겼다!
- 솔로몬!
- Victory!
- Solomon!
오늘밤, 우리는 다른 세상에 있어요
Tonight, we are alone in a different world.
나의 세상이에요
My world.
그렇소, 우리는 다른 세상에 있오
Yes, we are in a different world.
솔로몬! 전에 넌 내게 상속권을 빼앗았다
Solomon! Once before
you robbed me of my birthright,
포도주가 입에 맞지 않나요, 나의 주여?
Is not the wine to your taste, my Lord?
그러나 이번엔 포기하지 않는다!
but this time I'll not be denied!
당신이 파라오의 동맹국이란것을 거의 잊게 했다오
It almost made me forget
that you are an ally of the Pharaoh.
칼을 넣으시오
난 맹세를 깰수 없오
Sheathe your sword.
I will not break my pledge.
내 마음속에 간직하지
I will sheathe it in your heart.
이스라엘의 적을
An enemy of Israel.
폐하, 오늘밤 모든것이 준비됐습니다
Your Majesty,
everything is prepared for tonight.
전 이것을 선택했습니다
I chose this one.
음. 화향유(장미 기름), 난 그걸 좋아해
Mmm. Attar of roses. I love it.
- 왕께서 아주 좋아하는 향이에요
- 어떻게 알았지?
- The king's favourite scent.
- How do you know?
(groans)
그의 처소에 있는 여자들이 말해줬어요
The women of his harem told me.
난 그에게 다른 여자들이 생각나게 하고 싶지 않아
I don't want to remind him
of other women.
너는 그밖에 무엇을 들었느냐?
What else have you heard?
그들은 솔로몬이 그들에게 소홀히 하는걸 불평했어요
They complain
of Solomon's neglect of them.
아직 날 질투할 이유가 없다
There is no reason
to be jealous of me as yet.
그가 떠났지만 폐하를 잊는것이 어려울게 틀림없어요
In spite of the way he left,
he must have had difficulty forgetting you.
오늘밤, 심지어 나는 더 어렵게 만들거야
Tonight, I will make it even more difficult.
물기를 닦아라
Dry me.
폐하와 이스라엘이 지켜지리라고 믿는이가 예루살렘에 아무도 없었을때
When none in Jerusalem believed
that you and Israel could be saved,
그녀는 성전에 들어왔으며 지성소에서 당신께 용서받기를 기도하였습니다
she came into the temple and before the
sanctuary prayed you might be spared.
그가 올지 몰라요, 폐하
아직 한밤중이 아닙니다
He may still come, Majesty.
It is not yet midnight.
시간을 말하게 하기 위해 널 필요로 하는줄 아나?
Do I need you to tell me the time?
그것을 꺼내라
내 눈에서 사라지게 해
Take it away. Get it out of my sight.
어떻게 그가 나를 이처럼 다룰 용기가 있을까！
How dare he treat me this way!
그는 내가 무엇이라고 생각하지?
그의 창살에 갇힌 다른 고양이처럼?
What does he think I am?
Just another cat in his royal cage?!
그가 절대 오지 않아도 나는 마음에 두지 않아
I don't care if he never comes!
결코, 결코
Never. Never.
힘과 영광이 주를 위하여 있나이다
For thine is the power and the glory.
영원히
For ever.
그녀와 저녘식사를 하시기로 했지 않나요?
Weren't you supposed to dine with her?
암울한때에 내 이름을 부르니 내가 그 말을 들었노라
Because thou didst call upon my name
in thy dark hour, I have heard thee.
- 그랬소
- 그런데 왜 혼자 여기에 있죠?
- Yes, I was.
- Then why are you sitting here alone?
난 혼자 있는것이 필요하다고 느꼈다오
I felt in need of being alone.
네 자신의 땅으로 돌아가라
Return therefore until thine own land
무엇이 그렇게 당신 마음에 무거운 짐이 됐나요?
What is it that weighs
so heavily upon your heart?
그리고 네가 나와 한 약속을 지켜라
and keep the covenant
thou didst make with me.
내 생각들을 읽을수 있는 곳에서 왔오?
Has it come to where
you can read my thoughts?
난 항상 당신과 같은 생각들을 하고 있지 않았나요?
Haven't I always shared your thoughts?
그렇소
Yes.
때때로 사람은 그에게 직면하는 위험들에게 끌린다오
At times, a man feels drawn
toward the dangers that confront him,
심지어는 그 자신이 파멸하는 위험에도 불구하고
even at the risk of his own destruction.
나비가 불길에 접근하는것처럼
Like a moth approaches a flame.
이 불길에 관하여 다른 무엇인가가 있나요?
Is there something different
about this flame?
난 금새 몰아낼수 있었오
I could put it out in one second.
- 그것은 더 간단하지 않을까요?
- 아비삭, 그런 작은 불길에
- Wouldn't that be simpler?
- Such a little flame, Abishag.
지금 우리 사랑이 아이를 낳을거라고 말할수 있어요
Now I can tell you
that I am to bear the child of our love.
그런데 억제되지 않아, 그것은 이스라엘의 모든것을 파괴할수 있었소
And yet unrestrained,
it could destroy all of Jerusalem.
더 간단하게,
Simpler, yes,
그러나 아마도 그것 없이는
어둠이 있을것이요
but perhaps without it,
there would be darkness.
지금 그대는 이스라엘의 여왕이 될것이고 우리 아들은 나를 이어 다스리게 될것이오
Now you will be queen over Israel,
and our son shall reign after me.
아니에요
No.
빛 또는 어둠에서 당신은 단지 내손에 손을 뻗칠뿐이에요
In light or in darkness,
you've only to reach for my hand.
내 땅에 돌아가겠다고 하나님께 약속했어요
I gave promise to God
that I would return to my own land.
그 댓가로 하나님께서는 당신의 생명과 용서를 주셨어요
For that he granted me your life
and his forgiveness.
난 항상 당신의 옆에 있을거에요
I'll be at your side always.
그러나 어떻게 그대를 가게 할수 있겠오?
But how can I let you go?
당신의 아이는 시바를 다스리게 될거에요
Your child shall reign in the land of Sheba.
그리고 만일 하나님의 은혜로 아들을 주신다면
And if God grants us the blessing of a son,
잘 자요
잘 자시요
- Good night.
그때는 처음으로 시바는 왕을 갖게 될거에요
then for the first time
Sheba shall have a king,
그리고 그는 주 하나님 여호와의 길을 걸을거에요
and he shall walk in the way
of the Lord God Jehovah.
그것은 우리 속죄의 일부가 되어야 해요
That we must part is our atonement.
오, 하나님, 이것이 당신의 뜻이라면
If this be thy will, O God,
폐하
- His Majesty.
당신의 뜻에 따르겠나이다
I submit to thy judgement.
우리가 서로 떨어져 있을지라도
May thou watch between us
while we are apart, one from the other.
난 당신과 함께 있을것이에요........항상
I will be with you... always.
하나님께 소리쳐 외치노라, 온 세상이여, 그 이름의 영광을 찬양하라
Shout unto God, all the earth.
Sing praises unto the glory of his name.
오, 이스라엘이여, 주님을 찬양하라
Sing praises unto the Lord, O Israel.
자비로우신 하나님이시여
Be gracious unto us, God.
- 은총을 베푸소서
- And bless us.
(excited chatter)
(gong)
폐하
Sire.
그의 노여움은 순간이나
For his anger is but for a moment.
여왕폐하께서는 밤늦게 피곤할때까지 당신을 기다렸어요
Her Majesty awaited you until
after midnight and then she retired.
그의 사랑은 영원하도다
But his love is for ever.
미안하오
타칸, 폐하를 들어오시게 하라
- (Solomon) I'm sorry.
- Takyan, admit His Majesty.
밤에는 눈물이 머물렀으나
Weeping may tarry for a night,
아침에 즐거움이 밀려오는도다
but joy cometh in the morning.
당신의 휴식을 방해했군요
I have disturbed your rest.
아마 어떻게든 당신을 불쾌하게 했던 어떤 생각으로 내가 쉴수 있겠나요?
Could I rest, thinking that perhaps
I had displeased you in some way?
지금 당신은 나에게 솔직해야 하오
Now you have to be
completely truthful with me.
당신은 왜 예루살렘에 왔소?
Why did you come to Jerusalem?
왜 당신은 지금 내게 그런 질문을 하죠?
Why do you ask me such a question now?
그 아름다운 눈 뒤에 아주 똑똑한
여자의 두뇌가 있다는것을 알기 때문이요
Because I know that behind those lovely
eyes is the brain of a very clever woman
그리고 아무 목적도 없이 결코
800리그의 거리를 여행하지는 않았을것이오
who would never have travelled
800 leagues without a purpose.
눈치챘군요
You have found me out.
당신께 고백할께요
I will confess to you.
파라오는 당신을 정탐하는데 믿어지지 않는
댓가를 제게 지불하고 있어요
The Pharaoh is paying me
a fabulous price to spy on you.
당신의 비밀들을 모두 그에게 전달하는것으로
To deliver to him all of your secrets.
난 심사숙고하지만 정말로 이스라엘은 이집트에 대해 비밀이 없다오
I have considered that,
but Israel has no real secrets from Egypt.
파라오는 우리의 약함과 강함을 알고 있소
Pharaoh is aware
of our weaknesses and our strength.
어떻게 당신을 속이기를 바랄수 있었을까?
How could I hope to deceive you?
당신을 덫에 걸리게 하려고 했어요
I have been trying to entrap you.
이것들로
With these.
부드러운 사슬로 당신을 내게 붙들기 위해
내가 해야 할일을 할지도 모르죠
To bind you to me in soft chains
so that I may do with you as I will.
지금 아마도 우린 사실에 가까워지고 있을것이오
Now perhaps we are
approaching the truth.
모든 여자는 남자로부터 댓가를 강요하오
Every woman exacts her price
from a man.
당신은 여왕이지만 당신도 댓가를 요구하고 있오
You're a queen,
but you also demand a price.
그래요. 그래서 당신이 그것을 지불할것인지 매우 궁금하군요
I do. So great that I wonder
if you will pay it.
당신이 전적으로, 완전하게, 날 사랑하길 원해요
I want you to love me wholly, completely,
그리고 그 사랑이 당신의 인생에서 가장 귀중하게 되기를
and that love to be
the most precious thing in your life.
그것이 사실이기를 바라오
I hope it is true,
그러나 만일 그렇지 않다면
내가 사실을 모르는채로 머무르게 해주시오
but if it is not,
then let me remain blind to the truth.
당신이 나와 함께 있지 않았을때
그대를 자꾸 생각하는 날 볼수 있었소
Even when you are not with me,
I find myself trying to recall
매순간을 우린 함께 낭비했소
every moment we have spent together.
당신이 제게 한말은 결코 잊지 않겠다고 했죠
The words you have said to me,
I will never forget.
무언가 우리 사이를 지나가기 위해 온후에
내 마음에서 새로운 말들로 계속 노래하고 있소
After what has come to pass between us,
new words keep singing in my heart.
- 제게 그것을 말해봐요
- 보시오. 아름다운 그대, 내 사랑
- Tell them to me.
- Behold, thou art fair, my love.
그대의 눈은 비둘기 같고
그대의 입술은 석류향기 같구려
Thine eyes are as doves,
thy lips are as pomegranates.
그대의 사랑이 포도주 보다도 얼마나 더 좋은가
How much better is thy love than wine.
전에는 그런 행복을 알지 못했어요
I have never before
known such happiness.
행복했다는 생각을 가지고 있다면
나 자신을 속이는 것이라는것을 알고 있다오
Nor I, and if I have thought I was happy,
I know now that I was deceived.
그대들은 뱀들에 의해 부화되어 꺼내어진
두마리 새처럼 보이는군
You look like two birds
who have hatched out a nestful of snakes.
그대들은 자유로이 말할지 모르지만
난 요압에게 비밀이 없네
You may speak freely.
I have no secrets from Joab.
우리는 전하와 상의하기 위해 왔습니다
We have come to take counsel
with Your Highness.
무엇에 대해서? 난 군대의 지휘관이지 장관이 아니야
About what? I am the commander
of the host, not a minister of state.
왕과 관련이 있습니다
It concerns the king.
- 그렇다면 왜 왕과 상의하지 않지
- 왕께서 듣지 않을것이기 때문이죠
- Then why not consult with him?
- Because he will not listen.
왕에 대해 백성들로부터 심각한 비난들이 쏟아지고 있습니다
Grave criticism is being
brought against him by people.
누가 감히 위대한 솔로몬에 대하여 불평할 것인가?
Who would dare to murmur
against the great Solomon?
그의 시바여왕과의 교제는
공공연한 추문으로 발전하고 있습니다
His association with the Sheban queen
has developed into an open scandal.
더 안 좋은것은, 이 이방여자를
궁에서 살도록 데려와
Worse, he has even brought this
pagan woman to live within the palace,
감히 야영지를 그의 개인 거처에 인접하여 마련한것입니다
daring to install her in an apartment
adjoining his own private chambers.
그것은 그의 일이지, 나의 일이 아니다
That is his affair, not mine.
함께 계셨기 때문에 우린 전하께서 폐하께 개인적으로 말씀하신것으로 생각했습니다
We thought perhaps if you were to
talk to him privately, reason with him.
그것이 단지 고위 성직자에게만이
아니라 선지자와 중의회에도
Point out that it is a matter
of concern not only to the high priest
관련된 문제라는걸 지적해야 합니다
but to the prophet and the council.
내가, 감히 폐하께 경고를 한다?
I, presume to admonish His Majesty?
당신은 잊었소? 헤즈라이, 그는 왕이오
왕은 어떤 그릇된 일을 할수 없소
You forget, Hezrai, he is the king.
The king can do no wrong.
글쎄요, 무엇인가는 해야 합니다
Well, something must be done.
내가 아니라, 그의 재상인 헤즈라이
고위 성직자인 자독, 당신들이겠지
Not by me. You are his chancellor, Hezrai,
and you his high priest, Zadok.
여러분은 뭔가 해야 해요
그와 의논해야 합니다
You do something. You reason with him.
우리는 전하의 협력을 원했습니다
We had hoped for the cooperation
of Your Highness.
그대들에겐 충분한 능력이 있오
나의 바램과 강력한 소망이오
You have it.
My sympathies and my best wishes.
우리를 맞아 주셔서 감사합니다
We thank you for receiving us.
천만에, 천만에
Not at all, not at all.
항상 호의에 감사합니다
Always at your service.